<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The truth and certainty of the Protestant faith with a short and plain account of the doctrine of the Romish Church in its visible opposition to Scripture and the very being of Christianity : to which is adjoined some serious considerations anent popery &amp; the state of that controversy.</title>
            <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1277B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37829</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17061007</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17061007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39769)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1615:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The truth and certainty of the Protestant faith with a short and plain account of the doctrine of the Romish Church in its visible opposition to Scripture and the very being of Christianity : to which is adjoined some serious considerations anent popery &amp; the state of that controversy.</title>
                  <author>Fleming, Robert, 1630-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Rotterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Robert Fleming. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.) Sometimes erroneously attributed to Robert Fleming the younger.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105851:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105851:1"/>
            <p>THE Truth and Certainty of the PROTESTANT FAITH, With a ſhort and plain account of the Doctrine of the ROMISH CHURCH In its viſible Oppoſition to Scripture, and the very being of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is adjoined ſome ſerious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions anent Popery, &amp; the ſtate of that Controverſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>I. PET. III: Ver. 15.</bibl> And be ready alwayes to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>REVEL. XIV. Ver. 9.</bibl> If any man worship the Beaſt, or his Image, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eive his mark in his forehead, or in his hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Ver. 10.</bibl> The ſame shal drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is powred out without mixture into the cup of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he shall be tormented with fire and brimſtone, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the holy Angels and in the preſence of the Lamb.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Ver. 11.</bibl> And the ſmoak of their torment shall aſcend up for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and ever.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>squirrel eating</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105851:2"/>
            <head>EPISTLE <hi>To the</hi> CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe few ſheets adjoyned here against <hi>Popery,</hi> was in part formerly publiſhed, but being with ſome further enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now reprinted; I hope, it may not be found unſuteable to ſet them down here in the cloſe, when ſo convincing &amp; neceſſar a riſe from the foregoing ſubject is clear; though ſuch as deſire may have it by it ſelf alſo, without the preceeding treatiſe. Theſe grounds did in ſome meaſure preſſe me novv to the preſent publiſhing thereof. 1. That the import of this controverſy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Reformed Church,</hi> concernes the meanest this day no leſs than
<pb facs="tcp:105851:3"/> the more knowing and learned; and that to be a Proteſtant in earnest must neceſſarily require a ſeeing the truth with their ovvn eyes, yea ſuch a faith, as is the reſult of a judgment upon diligent ſearch convinced by the Scripture. 2. That it is an hour of great trial, and of the power of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; when the Popiſh Adverſary is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly at work almost every where to ſowe tares, whilst ſo fevv even of thoſe who ſeeme ſerious in profeſſing the truth, can give a clear account of the groſneſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and ſolide grounds of the Proteſtant Doctrine, when thus aſſaulted, but ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> naked thereto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as without defence, though abounding and clearest light hath been held forth for that end; and at a ſad diſavan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to hold fast their Profeſſion by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they ſhould be called thereto, as in former times. 3. The viſible hazard of many young ones in this generation to be made a prey of, and eaſily poiſoned vvith Popery, vvho but ſeldome vvork out in their age and riper years, vvhat they thus drink in in their youth. 4. That ſuch an eſſay ſeemed convincingly needful for theſe, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:105851:3"/> age, vvant of time, indiſpoſition to read, or loathneſs too be at expence in buying books, is too viſible a lett, for their improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what hath been more largely written by others. 5. That (as I hope it ſhall be found) vvhat is of greatest vveight or neceſſary uſe to be knovvn in theſe Controverſies, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere compriſed, though in ſmall bounds, yet vvith ſuch plainleſs, that the meanest Reader may underſtand and know the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and principles of Popery, and what <hi>Arguments</hi> they pretend to be most ſtrong, held forth in the <hi>Queſtions</hi> here propoſed; with a clear view of their direct oppoſition to the Scripture by the <hi>Anſwers</hi> thereto; ſo as in a very few houres, theſe for whom this is most deſigned, may by reading it but ſome times over, have it ſo far impreſſed on them, as to know how to anſwere, and give a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide account of the Proteſtant Doctrine, and groſneſs of Popery, when aſſaulted by any Seducers. If to any ſuch this ſmall eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay might be of uſe, I may then ſay, the <hi>Author</hi> hath not lost his deſire and aime, what ever entertainment it ſhould other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe meet with. The time haſteneth, when
<pb facs="tcp:105851:4"/> that only, vvhich tendeth to a ſolide peace with Jeſus Christ vvill abide, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y near to the ſoul vvhen the Teſtimony of men will be of ſmall value.</p>
            <p>I ſhall but add, that nothing is here charged on the Romiſh Adverſary, as their principles. Which their own greatest Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, of the Doctrine of the <hi>Councel of Trent</hi> do not clearly attest. The Reader vvould conſider, that theſe <hi>Sections</hi> into vvhich this is divided, is vvith reſpect to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Doctrine,</hi> vvhich are there handled.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>There are ſeveral Miſtakes in words from the preſs, which I hope, the judicious Reader will diſcerne, without having the ſenſe darkned thereby, and pardon, with ſome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Miſtakes alſo in the pointing.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105851:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing our greateſt intereſt, is to know the truth and certainty of that Religion we profeſs, What is to be underſtood</hi>
                  </hi> by the Proteſtant Reformed Religion, <hi>as under ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation it is now held forth? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> The Scripture, unto whoſe trial this offereth it ſelf, clearly ſheweth, that it is no new Doctrine brought in on the World, but the truth of Chriſtianity, by the good hand of the Lord on the Reformed Church, confeſſed, aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and purged from the corruptions of Popery; and hath the very ſame grounds to prove it, which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion hath. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is it not of late, the Name of</hi>
                  </hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, <hi>much leſs as a Church, was known, and from viſible appearances but little, to evidence its being and ſucceſſion in the World, when Popery for many Ages had a conſpicuous and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing State? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> We deny not the <hi>Reformation</hi> to be late, and that name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> which hath its riſe from a ſolemne <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> of ſeveral Princes and Cities againſt <hi>Popery:</hi> But theſe alſo are demonſtrably clear. 1. How it is the ſame truth, and Religion of the Apoſtles and Primitive<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Church, wherein they walked, though in a great meaſure after darkned, as <hi>Antichriſtianiſme</hi> grew up; which hath been unanſwerably, proved to the World. 2. That in the Scripture no ground can be ſhewed, for a continual viſibility of the Church, as an unite body; and in a flouriſhing outward ſtate; but the contrary is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, how obſcure, &amp; low her condition ſhould be dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Antichriſt's</hi> reign: So as <hi>a place of hiding was then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for her, Rev.</hi> 12: 6. 3. Yet even in the darkeſt times, there did not want ſome viſibility of the true Church, by a continued ſucceſſion of witneſſes to appear for the Truth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105851:5"/> and againſt the Romiſh Apoſtacie, which, as a freſh Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, made its way through that horride Lake, without mixing with it. <hi>Qu. <hi>What peculiar grounds are to prove this, or enforce a conviction on others. That the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, this day, is the pure, and ancient Chriſtian Religion?</hi> Anſ.</hi> If men ſhut not their eyes, none can deny theſe grounds, as a teſt of the certainty thereof. 1. Its exact con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Scripture, and to the genuine and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſenſe thereof, than which nothing is more clear, if we will, but compare theſe together. 2. That the Proteſtant Religion, in all the eſſentials thereof, is the very ſame, and exactly agrees with the Faith of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, in the firſt three centuries; and for this we appeal our adverſaries to produce one eſſential difference, betwixt the one and the other from the Records of theſe times, or any Writings of the Fathers. 3. That no evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can be given, in contending for the Chriſtian Faith againſt Heathens, and to hold forth the certainty thereof, which doth not undeniably anſwer to confirm the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion. 4. That in the writings of the greateſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, &amp; their bitter invectives againſt Chriſtianity, who in the firſt times did oppoſe themſelves to the ſame Doctrine the Proteſtant Church now owns, and profeſſeth; ſuch as <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſus, Tryphon, Porphyrie, Lucian,</hi> &amp;c. There is not the leaſt mention of Popery, in any of theſe Articles, againſt which the Proteſtant Church contends, nor of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Supremacy and Infallibility, where they could have had ſo great advantage to object againſt the Chriſtian Cauſe, and call its Truth in queſtion: Nor did the Jews who objected all they could againſt the Chriſtian Faith, in the leaſt once mention any ſuch points as are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted betwixt them and us. 5. It is clear from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Hiſtorie, and confeſſion of our Adverſaries, that a continued ſucceſſion of Orthodox Doctors, who did confeſſe and teach the ſame Doctrine, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that we own, have in no times been wanting to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105851:5"/> the Church, nor ſome viſible partie to withſtand <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and keep up a witneſſe to the Truth, even in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt darkneſſe; as the Romiſh Writers are forced to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, That the Proteſtants now are the ſame which the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> were of old, and the <hi>Berengarians</hi> before them. <hi>Qu. <hi>Doth not the Popiſh Religion found on ſuch grounds and Principles, as can bring a ſufficient certainty therewith of its Truth, when it hath the Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es, Canons, and infallible Deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Church, to warrant the ſame, and of the Pope as Supreme Head? </hi>Anſ.</hi> According to their Doctrine &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, they can have no poſſible certaintie of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor of that they pretend to found on: When, 1. They are not agreed, nor ever like to be, who that infallible Judge is; or in whom ſuch an Infallibilitie as they claim is ſeated, whether in a General Council, or the Pope alone: So as they are in greateſt contradiction to other, about the very foundation of their Faith; nor is this a controverſie amongſt a few, but one part of their Church, with greateſt heat, is oppoſing the other therein. 2. They can have no aſſurance if they have any Church at all, and whether moſt of their Popes, Biſhops and Prieſts, be not without Baptiſm, and ſtill laicks without Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, when their Doctrine, and the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſo expreſlie hold the efficacie of all Sacraments (of which they reckon Ordination as well as Baptiſm to be one) to depend on the Intention of the Prieſt who officiates, of which none poſſiblie can be ſure. 3. Such have no ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal certaintie of what they profeſſe to believe, who are with their own conſent ſhut out from all proper knowledge of the Scripture, and on the teſtimonie of men muſt reſolve their Faith. 4. Is it not on a matter of fact, and moſt doubtful Relation, they ground their Faith, and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their immortal ſoul, where ſcarce a Shadow, or School-problem is to bear up the whole Fabrick of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; which is an alledged Preſidence of <hi>Peter</hi> amongſt the Apoſtles, while no demonſtration can ever be given, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105851:6"/> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> or that he was Biſhop there, or if the ſame priviledges be intailed to his Succeſſours, and how theſe ſhould be choſen in after-times? 5. According to their Principles, they have no <hi>Bible,</hi> nor any ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Record, to prove Religion, but what is a Maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of dead unſenſed Characters, that hath no articulate voice or intelligible ſound, until the Romiſh Clergie put a ſenſe thereon: So that the verie Letter of the Scripture is moſt evidentlie paſt from: For my ſelf, I dare ſay, before him who knoweth all things, that I would tremble and ſtand in a we of any deceit or miſtake, in the matter of Religion, and have in greateſt earneſt ſought to be perſwaded of the Truth, without reſpect to intereſt, party, or education, as that wherein I know an eternal ſalvation is concerned; but can ſee no way to embrace Poperie, except men turn Atheiſts, yea, quit all Religion and Reaſon at once. <hi>Qu, <hi>Is not</hi> Rome <hi>the Catholick and Apoſtolick Church, out of which there is no Salvation?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know there is a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church under the Goſpel, that conſiſts of all who imbrace the Chriſtian Faith, whether bond or free, Jewes or Gentiles, and is to no particular Nation, People, or language, reſtricted, as under the Law: But that the Romiſh Church can have no poſſible claim here, is unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Becauſe no Inſtitution is in the Scripture of ſuch a Church, as conſiſteth of all Chriſtians ſubjected to one humane Head, and Supreme Governour under Jeſus Chriſt, on the Earth; or where ſubjection to the Pope is made a condition to Salvation. 2. It is clear that in the Apoſtles time, and for many Ages after, the Chriſtian Catholick Church had a being, when it had no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor was known by any ſuch Teſt, as to own the Pope and his Supreme Juriſdiction; except it be averred, that there was one Catholick Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſetting up of Papacy, and the other ſince, eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially different from the former. 3. There is no acceſſe to deny, that they are more, and of greater extent in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105851:6"/> world, who embrace the Chriſtian Faith, and have no communion with the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or their Doctrine, than ſuch who are ſubjected thereto. 4. As there is on <hi>Faith, and one Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> ſo is there but <hi>one body, which is his Church,</hi> united to him as her Head, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4: 3. 4. Which is the prorogative of the Son of God alone, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to any, to be the Head thereof, but <hi>he who for this end died and roſe, that he might be the Lord of the dead and of the living,</hi> Rom. 14: 9. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet is not ſtill the ſame Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, at leaſt for ſubſtance, held forth in the Popiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Doctrine, which the Proteſtant Church owns?</hi> Anſ.</hi> Whatever in words ſuch pretend, their Principles, and the known Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> can too viſibly reſolve this, that theſe do not retain the Chriſtian Faith, in the eſſentials thereof, but have razed the very foudation, who reſolve not their Faith on the Scripture and its Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but on a humane teſtimony; and deny religious worſhip to be due to the true God alone, but give it unto Angels and Men alſo; who lay another foundation to build on than Jeſus Chriſt, another Purgatorie than his blood, to purifie us from all ſin, another Propitiatorie Sacrifice to expiate ſin, than his Death, who <hi>was once offered to bear the ſins of many.</hi> Heb. 9: 28: another merite than his obedience, by which we are made righteous; and thus make void the great intent of the Goſpel laying down a way of Life and Salvation on the ſame terms that it ſtood in the Covenant of works; certainly we muſt either quite the Scriptures, or acknowledge that nothing can be more deſtructive to the Chriſtian Faith revealed there, than ſuch Doctrine. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is there no infallible Rule and Judge, to determine herein, on whoſe deciſive ſentence we may ſecurely reſt in the greatest controverſies?</hi> Anſ.</hi> If we own ourſelves Chriſtians, this can be no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, that the Scriptures contained in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtament</hi> are the ſupreme Judge, <hi>The Oracles of God</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3: 2. to give Anſwers in every dark caſe; <hi>The Type and forme of ſound Doctrine, Rom.</hi> 6: 17.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105851:7"/> Unto whoſe ſentence we are, in all matters both of Faith and Practice, expreſly referred by the Lord <hi>Iſaiah 8: 20. To the Law and to the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>SInce the Rule of Faith muſt be plain and intelligible, can the Scripture be ſuch, which, according to the</hi>
                  </hi> Popiſh Doctrine, <hi>is a</hi> Maſſe <hi>of dead and dark Characters, untill their Church put a ſenſe thereon? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> Its own witneſſe, is clear, 1. That it <hi>Is ſuch as maketh the ſimple wiſe, Pſal.</hi> 19: 7. And a <hi>Light ſhining in a dark place,</hi> to which we are called <hi>to take heed, 2 Pet, 1: v. 19. A Lamp to our feet, Pſal.</hi> 119: 105. 2. We ſee, what is written there <hi>was for our learning, Rom.</hi> 15: 4. and given us for that end, that it might be underſtood. 3. It is clear, the promiſe of the <hi>Spirit to lead us into all Truth, Joh.</hi> 16: 13. doth belong to every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, as well as to the greateſt Doctors of the Church, who can pretend no extraordinary Revelation for leading of them. 4. We know, the Fathers and Ancient Church did ſtill prove their Doctrine from the Scripture, as not only of more authority, but more clear than their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 5. Though ſome Scriptures be not ſo plain as others, and ſeveral Prophecies ſealed up, until their tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place in the event; yet, nothing can be more plain than the fundamentals of Chriſtianity, and thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Truths neceſſary to Salvation: But the World may ſee it is not obſcurity, againſt which their true quarrel is, but a too clear evidence, before which their intereſt cannot ſtand. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet, is this a ſufficient ground, for the Scriptures being tranſlated into our own Language, ſo as every Man may read, and have acceſs thereto, which the</hi> Romiſh Church <hi>ſo expreſly forbids, as the cauſe of Error and Hereſie?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know 1. The command is expreſs for all to read, and <hi>teach their children, Deut.</hi> 6: 11. 2. That under the Law, the Jewiſh Church had no reſtraint; and ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105851:7"/> the Church now be in a worſe caſe, and live in more darkneſſe? 3. Upon this account, were the <hi>Bereans</hi> ſo highly commended for examining the Apoſtles Doctrine, by the written Word, which they could never have done, if any ſuch reſtraint to read the ſame had been upon them. 4. It is a ſtrange cure, to keep from the Light for fear of going wrong; and when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>You erre not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> 22: 22. That ignorance thereof ſhould be the way to keep us right. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is it not evident, 2 Pet. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v: 16. How there are things hard to be underſtood in</hi> Paul's <hi>Epiſtles, which the unlearned and unſtable wreſt to their own deſtruction?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is there ſhewed: 1. Some things are more dark in the Scripture, which none do deny. 2. We ſee, thoſe who thus ſtumble, are ſuch as wreſt the Word, and not of a humble, ſober, and ſerious Spirit, by whom none will judge the Apoſtle here means the whole of Believers within the Church, except the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors thereof: Nor hath it more weight to forbid Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians uſe of the Scriptures, and to read the ſame; than the neceſſary uſe of meat, becauſe ſome unſober abuſe the ſame to their hurt. <hi>Qu. <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t inducement ſhould the Romiſh Church have to reſtrain Chriſtians in this, if it be ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly croſs to the Rule?</hi> Anſ.</hi> They have (I confeſs) this plea, for neceſſity; ſince their caſe ſo ſtands, they muſt either ruine their intereſt, and be diſcovered in the greateſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture that ever was known in the World; or have the <hi>Bible</hi> ſhut up, though to ruine the Souls of many Millions of the poor People; nor is it ſtrange ſuch hate the light, whoſe deeds are evil, leſt they be reproved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS it not to the Church, and to no private perſon, That the ſupreme Authority, and power of interpreting the Scripture, and to be judge of the true ſenſe thereof, doth belong?</hi> Anſ.</hi> The Scriptures is the alone infallible Rule for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting it ſelf: And to none but to the Holy Ghoſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105851:8"/> to us there, can ſuch Authority be aſcribed. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Scripture is the ſupreme ſtandard, by which we are called <hi>to prove all things, 1 Theſ.</hi> 5: 21. and <hi>to know the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, whether they be of God or not, 1 Joh.</hi> 4: 1. Yea, thus muſt the Doctrine of the Church be known. 2. The ſenſe of the Scripture is the Scripture it ſelf, which thence only can be ſought, and underſtood by the ſame Spirit, that indited it. 3. We ſee by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> innumerable inſtances, that where in one place it ſpeaks more darkly, it doth explain it ſelf in another, and thus refers us to its own interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yea, how with a greater light and plainneſſe Truths are opened up in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which more darkly, and as under a Vail, were held forth in the <hi>Old. <hi>Qu.</hi> But the Scripture is of no private interpretation, therefore to the Church only it muſt belong? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> This only ſhews the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Interpretation can be ſubjected to no humane Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor hath its Authority of men, and from their private judgements, whatever place they bear in the Church; but muſt be ſought from the Scripture it ſelf, and according to the Analogie of Faith, but no ground in the leaſt to deny acceſſe to private perſons, to know and ſeek after the true ſenſe of the Scripture. <hi>Qu. <hi>What aſſurance can any have, that ſuch is the true ſenſe of the Scripture, without ſome authoritative deciſion of the Church?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know, 1. That the promiſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7: 17. ſtands good to every one of the Saints, <hi>If any man do my will, he ſhall know my Doctrine, whether it be of God or not:</hi> And ſuch who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject this, dare not (I am ſure) reſtrict the giving of the Spirit for that end to their <hi>Church-Doctors</hi> onlie. 2. If the ſenſe of any thing written can be underſtood, then it is ſure the moſt weighty and neceſſarie truths of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are ſo obviouſlie plain, as they can bear no other ſenſe and meaning, except men quit the very uſe of Reaſon and Judgement. 3. Where the Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is more dark, there want not peculiar helps and means for a Chriſtians attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true ſenſe thereof, ſuch as ſerious prayer; the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105851:8"/> knowledg of the original languages, and repairing to theſe fountains themſelves; advertency to the ſcope, and intent of the Scripture; yea, a dexterous comparing of one place with another; with a prudent uſe of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and commentaries of ſuch, as have written there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though not implicitely to reſt upon them. <hi>Qu. <hi>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hath not the Scripture ſo various ſenſes, as neceſſarily requires a living and viſible Judge, to decide when to take it in a literal, or in a figurative ſenſe?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It concerns the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> to impoſe divers ſenſes on the Scripture, that it may have none at all: though we deny not ſome figurative expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the true ſenſe whereof muſt be underſtood from what is the obvious intent as the ſcope of ſuch a Scripture, &amp; not the very words themſelves. Such as <hi>Mat. 5: 29. If thine eye offend thee pluck it out.</hi> Pſal. 91: 13. <hi>Thou ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tread upon the lion, and the dragon:</hi> But it is moſt clear. 1. That one true and genuine ſenſe the Scripture only hath, from the words rightly underſtood, which is the literal ſenſe, and thence only Arguments can be taken to prove any truth. 2. That in truths neceſſary to Salvation is no thing figuratively expreſſed, but what is with greateſt plainneſſe, to the diſcerning of all, held forth, 3. What the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> pleads for, of an <hi>Allegorick, Moral</hi> and <hi>Typical</hi> ſenſe, they are no different ſenſes of the Scripture, but a different application and accommodation of one and the ſame Scripture divers ways, in the uſe whereof much cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſobriety is needful: and though a neceſſarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is to be had always to the Type, and the thing Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; yet, even there, is the ſenſe ſtill one and the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>HOw know you the Scripture is of God, or can be infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly ſure of its Divinity. but by the Church and its Teſtimony?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We deny not this to be a peculiar motive and inducement, for a high and reverent eſteem thereof, and a miniſterial help to our Faith, though with no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105851:9"/> Dominion over the ſame. But 1. The Scripture is known by its own light, and theſe expreſſe Characters and marks of Divinity it bears, which convincingly ſhew whoſe it is; ſo as the meaneſt Chriſtian may know this, without any humane Teſtimony. 2. There needs alſo the inward work of the Spirit, to beget a firm and through perſwaſion thereof upon the Soul. <hi>Qu. <hi>But how do you know, you perceive ſuch a light in the Scriptures, as you ſpeak of? Or can make it appear to others, that you are not deceived therein?</hi> Anſ.</hi> None will diſtruſt their own eves, though by no Arguments they can perſwade thoſe, who are blind, that they really behold ſo excellent a light as the Sun: But it is ſtrange and abſurd, to demand a reaſon of Senſe; or for a blind man, to require him who ſeeth, to prove unto him by Argument, that he certainly ſees and beholds ſuch things. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not this torun in a round and circle, from the Scripture to the Spirit, &amp; from the Spirit again to the Scripture, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s you know by the Spirits revealing the Scripture to be the Word of GOD, and that revelation to be true by the Scripture?</hi> Anſ.</hi> No ground is here for any ſuch challenge. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we admit no private or particular Revelation of the Spirit, to aſſure us of the Truth, different from what is revealed in the Scripture it ſelf. 2. It can be no circle, when it is ſo clear, the Scripture and Spirit mutually prove one another, by different wayes, and not in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; for it is by way of <hi>Argument,</hi> that the Scripture proves the certainty of the Spirit, holding out ſuch truths, whence we know how to diſcern the Spirit; but <hi>effectively,</hi> and as an inſtrument doth the Spirit prove the Scripture, by enabling us to ſee that marvelous light, which is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. 3. As hath been already cleared, there are Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of another nature, and independent on the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Spirit, by which the Divinity of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can be ſolidly known and demonſtrated. <hi>Qu. <hi>Can you know the Scripture is Canonical, or that theſe Apocrypha Books, which</hi> Proteſtants <hi>reject, are no part thereof, without the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105851:9"/> Churches deciſion?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know, 1. That theſe were never acknowledged in the Canon of the Scripture, by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church before Chriſt, to which the Oracles of God were committed; nor read and expounded in their Synagogues, as their moſt Ancient Writers and of the greateſt credit amongſt them witneſſe. 2. They were not written in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the language of the Church, before the coming of Chriſt, in which all the Books of the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> were generally written. 3. Though with that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere caution, was the Ancient Church careful to keep the Scripture, ſo as the number of the verſes &amp; letters thereof was moſt exactly re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>koned, and lookt to; yet none of theſe Apocryphal Books was ever received, or admitted by them. 4. By the Primitive Church, after the Apoſtles, ſuch were not owned in the Canon of the Scripture, though by ſome allowed to be read for inſtruction of manners. 5. They are convict of notorious falſhood in many places, both of Doctrine and Hiſtory, which all may ſee repugnant to Truth, and the Analogy of Faith. <hi>Qu. <hi>Bus what certainty can be, on the credit of a Tranſlation, that all know to be fallible?</hi> Anſ.</hi> Nothing can be more, for moral aſſurance, when it is ſo clear. 1. That the truth of our tranſlations, though in divers times and different Languages, yet all agree in the maine and ſubſtance. 2. That ſolide relief is at hand, to go unto the fountains themſelves, the original Languages, and ſee with their own eyes, if the Tranſlations thereof be not faithful and true; which by a little pains, and diligent uſe of helps for ſuch an end, is in our power to attain. 3. It is not on naked words, but on the clear and genuine ſenſe thereof, in whatever Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage held forth, that we found our Faith; nor can any deny the Scripture truely rendered in Engliſh to be the Word of God, though not in the very ſame Characters, in which the Prophets wrote the ſame. 4. Theſe evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the Scriptures Divinity, that it enlighteneth the eyes, and converts the Soul, with its Authority over
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105851:10"/> the Conſcience, we know to be no leſs diſcernably, and convincingly witneſſed in mens vulgar Language, through all ages, than in the <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS the Scripture of a ſufficient foundation of Faith, for a private Chriſtian, which according to the Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine must have its A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thority from the Church without which it can be no Scripture, nor Canonical?</hi> Anſ.</hi> They are indeed concerned to put down all Divine Record, that they may be alone Judges in their own cauſe: But we know, 1. That the Apoſtolick Church had no ſuch claim. 2 <hi>Cor. 1: 24. Not that we have dominion over your Faith.</hi> 2. That they did bound their Authority within the limits of the Scripture; <hi>Gal. 1: 8. Though we, or an Angel from Heaven, preach ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrine than that we have preached to you, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi> 3. Thus ſhould the Churches witneſſe be of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter credit and weight, then the Word of God. 4: There is no Authority, even the Romiſh Church can pretend to, but what they plead from the Scripture; therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be dependent upon the Church. 5. Should this be admitted, the Chriſtian cauſe were loſt, in contending againſt Atheiſts and Infidels; nor any poſſible acceſs to convince theſe: for what could that Argument of the Church's Authority be to them, who own no ſuch thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. If on this the Scripture be admitted, our Faith ſhould then reſolve on the Teſtimony of men, and be but a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith. <hi>Qu. <hi>But must every private Man be his own Judge, and not the Church, to put what ſenſe he pleaſeth on the Scripture?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is clear, 1. That there is a private judgement of diſcretion the meaneſt Chriſtian hath, to know and diſcern the Truth, that his ſervice may be <hi>Reaſonable ſervice, Rom.</hi> 12: 1. And his Faith a rational act, <hi>For every man muſt prove his own work, Gal.</hi> 6: 4. 2. We deny not a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick and miniſterial judgement to the Church, which in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105851:10"/> greater and leſſet Synods may be paſſed, where Paſtors &amp; Elders are aſſembled by the ordinance of Chriſt, though here no blind obedience is impoſed; ſince this only can be according to the Law, and in purſuance of it, not above it. But to the Holy Ghoſt alone, can a Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and a Soveraignty of judgement, in matters of Faih, belong; Since. <hi>There is but one Lawgiver, who is able to ſave and deſtroy,</hi> Jam. 4: 12. <hi>And no power against the truth, but for it, 2 Cor.</hi> 13: 8. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are we not called to hear the Church, Mat. 18: 17. and implicitely rely on its ſentence?</hi> Anſ.</hi> That command hath reſpect to Church-cenſure, and againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacie; but to impoſe no implicite obedience, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Scripture Authority to Men: When it is ſo clear, 1. That the furtheſt obſervance of the Apoſtle was to be ſuch, as might not go without theſe bounds, <hi>Be ye follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of me, as I am of Chriſt.</hi> 2. This were to divide Faith and Knowledge from one another, and an expreſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting of that, 1 <hi>Pet. 3: 15. To be ready to give a reaſon of faith within us, to every who demands.</hi> 3. Thus Men might be ſaved without believing there is a Chriſt and the Goſpel. 4. Thus many were under a neceſſity to live and die Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, if they muſt only hear what the Romiſh Church ſayes, &amp; not read the Scripture themſelves, who in ſome remote parts of earth, or by a cloſe impriſonment may be ſhut up, ſo as they can have no poſſible converſe with that Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS there no Supreme, Viſible, and Infallible Judge, placed in the Church, upon whoſe deciſion we may ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely reſt, in all matters of Faith and Conſcience?</hi> Anſ.</hi> This Article is indeed of great weight to the Romiſh Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo as their whole intereſt ſeems to ſtand or fall accordingly: But it is clear, 1. They muſt bring another <hi>Bible</hi> than the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to prove this, or let us ſee the leaſt Commiſſion and Warrant, for any ſuch Judge there, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105851:11"/> they plead for. 2. It is contrary to the command, 1 <hi>Theſ. 5: 21. Prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> 3. None can deny the Apoſtles were fallible, though not in their Doctrine, (being therein immediatly inſpired by the holy Ghoſt) when ſo ignorant of the Death, Sufferings, and Reſurrection of Chriſt; and it is ſure, <hi>Peter</hi> was far from this Infallibility, when he denied his Maſter; and after he was confirmed, and had that aſſurance given, that his Faith ſhould not fail, (which is one great foundation of the pretended Romiſh Infallibility) when <hi>Paul withſtood him to the face, Gal.</hi> 2: 11. 4. This power doth the Pope challeng over the Gentiles, as being <hi>Peter's</hi> ſucceſſor; when it is clear, that <hi>Paul</hi> was the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, by the appointment of the Holy Ghoſt, and <hi>Peters</hi> own conſent, <hi>Rom. 11: 17. Acts 13: 2. Gal.</hi> 2: 9. 5. And do not all know, what decrees of Councils have been againſt Councils and Popes againſt Popes? <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not</hi>
                  </hi> Peter <hi>that Rock, on which Christ promiſed to build the Church?</hi> Mat. 16: 18. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is manifeſt, that by this was expreſly meant the Doctrine, and Profeſſion then made of Chriſt's being the Son of God; yea, that the ſame power given to <hi>Peter</hi> was, in as expreſſe termes, given to the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Mat. 18: 18. Ioh.</hi> 20: 22. And where it is ſaid, <hi>Ye are built upon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Eph.</hi> 2: 20. no difference is in the leaſt put betwixt <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt: yet here is the great foundation of their Church. <hi>Qu. <hi>Does not this prove ſuch an Infallibility, that the Church is</hi>
                  </hi> the Pillar and ground of Truth, 1 Tim 3: 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This was not ſaid of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or evince her peculiar claim thereto beyond other Churches; But here cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arlie is ſhewed the ſtability and fixedneſſe of the Chriſtian Church, unto which the Oracles of God were committed; and no poſſible reaſoning thence, for an Infallibility to any Church on Earth. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is there nothing from the Scripture, to ſhew a difference betwixt</hi> Peter <hi>and the reſt of the Apoſtles, as to his Preſidence, and that the Monarchie of the Church was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105851:11"/> eſtabliſhed in his perſon?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We find this was expreſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by Jeſus Chriſt to the whole Apoſtles, without exception, that no ſuch abſolute Authority ſhould be by any of them claimed? <hi>Mat. 23: 10: Be ye not called maſters, for one is your maſter even Chriſt:</hi> But if any ſhadow were for this, It might ſeem more applicable to <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Beſides theſe, the care of all the Churches came upon me, 2 Cor. 11: v.</hi> 28. If this had been ſaid of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Romiſh writers would have made a ſtrange noiſe; as if they had found one demonſtration for all, to ſecure that intereſt,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>CAn the Scripture be a ſufficient Rule of Faith, and ſufficient to decide controverſies in the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of unwritten Traditions?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is; 1. Becauſe <hi>the alone way</hi> for being ſaved is in following what is written there, <hi>Ioh. 20: 31. Theſe things are written, that you may believe that Ieſus is the Chriſt, and that believing you might have life through his name.</hi> 2. It is a full and ſufficient Rule, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all things neceſſary, both to believe &amp; do; 2 <hi>Tim. 3. 15. From a Child thou haſt known the holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation, through faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> Yea, it is there ſhewed to be <hi>Profitable for Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi> 3. It is expreſly againſt the Scriptures, to impoſe any humane Traditions on the Church, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting our Faith thereto. <hi>Deut, 4: 2. <hi>Thou ſhalt not add to the words, which I command thee. <hi>Qu.</hi> But doth not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle command to hold faſt the Traditions, whether by Word or Epistle delivered to us?</hi> 2. Theſ. 2: 15? <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is there ſhewed. 1. That the Apoſtolick Authority, whether in ſpeaking, or writing, was the ſame; and that to both the Church was to give the ſame credit. 2. That what was taught from the Apoſtle by word, was the very ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105851:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> by Epiſtle: but thence can be no ground for receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Traditions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are not only different from the Scripture, but viſibly con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, when neither Scripture, Reaſon, nor Antiquity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their being delivered by the Apoſtles. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not</hi> Oral <hi>Tradition ſuch as cannot poſſibly deceive, whereby the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, and true ſenſe of the Scripture hath been delivered down from hand to hand, and from one age to another?</hi> Anſ.</hi> To this of late doth a part of this of late doth a part of the Romiſh Church fly, though nothing more viſibly repugnant to Scripture and Reaſon, if men but open their eyes, to ſee, 1. That no more ſure, and plain delivery of the Truth can be to us by ſpeaking, than by writing; nor can it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly judged, how a certainty of the ſenſe of their traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Doctrine ſhould be more than that of the Scripture. 2. This were to reſolve our Faith; not on the Teſtimony of God in his Word, but on what the Father &amp; Forefathers have told to the Children; and in effect to paſs from all cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Chriſtian Faith, and to deny that Doctrine of Chriſt, and, way of being eternally ſaved, which, with moſt convincing evidence, is delivered to us in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 3. We ſee, how far <hi>Tradition</hi> in a few Ages differeth from it ſelf, and hath been the riſe of ſuch fabulous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances the World is full of about matters of fact, from former times; yea, how oft the Church hath been almoſt ſwallowed up of ignorance and errour: ſo that if one would trace back the <hi>Divinity of Christ</hi> by Tradition, they ſhould go near to loſe the ſcent, when it came to <hi>Athanaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s's</hi> time, whilſt the whole Chriſtian world ſeemed to be <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. <hi>Qu.</hi> Is there no neceſſity of Tradition, when the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not ſufficient to refute all Hereſies in the Church?</hi> Anſ.</hi> Can it be poſſible to underſtand Hereſies, but as they are againſt the Scripture, or how to have another conception thereof, and yet that not ſufficient for their refutation? this is, I confeſſe, a Doctrine meet for ſuch, who can make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions meet and agree at their pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105851:12"/>
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>HAve we not ſafe and unanſwerable ground, from the Antiquity of the Romiſh Doctrine, and its long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſucceſſion, to found an infallible aſſurance of its Truth?</hi> Anſ.</hi> None can deny theſe, 1. That the Scripture is the trueſt Antiquity, and what is not according to this, is a novelty brought in on the Church. 2. That the riſe and pedegree of the Man of Sin muſt be trac'd back to the very times of the Apoſtles, in his beginning to work, whoſe gradual breaking-up did then haſten to a more full appearance. 3. But it is moſt clear alſo, that the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, for ſome Ages, knew no ſuch thing as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, in ſo horrid a corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of the Chriſtian Doctrine, that after followed; nor what an Univerſal Biſhop, and his Infallibility meaned. <hi>Qu. <hi>But can any evidence be found from theſe firſt times of the Chriſtian Church, that will import a contradicting of the Popiſh Doctrine, as it is now profeſſed.</hi> Anſ.</hi> There are no accidents where the thing it ſelf hath no being, nor could theſe poſſibly write againſt Poperie, in ſuch heads, as the Romiſh Infallibility, the worſhip of Images and Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before they were once brought to light: but by undeniable conſequence it is clear, they held the <hi>Scripture</hi> to be the <hi>alone Rule,</hi> and foundation of the Chriſtian Faith; therefore not the <hi>Romiſh Church:</hi> and that the Counſel of God was clearly revealed in the ſame; therefore not to be ſhut up as the fountain of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: Yea, that there are but two places after death, without the leaſt touch, or mentioning ſuch a thing as <hi>Purgatory.</hi> This alſo was the known Doctrine of the firſt times, that Faith in Chriſt was the alone way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; therefore not by o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>own merit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105851:13"/>
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS not the Doctrine of Merit, for which the Romiſh Church ſo much contend, agreeable to the Scripture, and ſuch as we may ſecurely reſt upon; That men by their own Righteouſneſs, and the merit of works may be ſaved?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is clear, we muſt go to Heaven by Merit, though not our own; yea, upon the exacteſt terms of Juſtice, it is due to him, who hath paid the price to the utmoſt value, that none of his purchaſe be loſt; but to us it is only of Grace: Nor can ſuch Works be meritorious, where, 1. We owe all, and do nothing which is not a debt upon us, being <hi>Not our own, but bought with a price, 1 Cor.</hi> 6: 17. 2. Where no equality, proportion, or ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can be betwixt the Work and the Reward; as is clear, 2 <hi>Cor. 4: 17. Rom.</hi> 3: 28. 3. Which at the beſt have ſome ſpot, and ſtain cleaving thereto, and come ſo ſhort to anſwer what the Law requires, <hi>Iſa. 64: 4. But we are all as an unclean thing, and all our righteouſneſs as filthy rags.</hi> 4. It is moſt directly contrary to the Scripture, <hi>Rom. 11: 6. If by grace, it is no more of works, otherwiſe grace is no more grace,</hi> Rom. 4: 4. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w to him that worketh is the reward not reckoned of grace, but of debt; but to him who worketh not, but believeth in him who juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs;</hi> and chap. 3: 28. <hi>Wherefore we conclude, that we are juſtified by faith, without the deeds of the Law. <hi>Qu.</hi> Yet, may not ſome in an unconverted ſtate deſerve a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of Grace upon them, by putting themſelves forth to the utmoſt for their own converſion, which the Romiſh Church call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the</hi> Merit of congruity? <hi>Anſ.</hi> From the Scripture it is clear, that before renewing Grace, all are the Children of wrath, who of themſelves, cannot frame their thoughts to that which is good, nor have an active concurrence for ſuch a change, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3: 5. And that the alone cauſe, which maketh one to differ from another, is that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105851:13"/> 
                  <hi>verſ. 15. I will have mercy, on whom I will have mercy.</hi> Therefore no plea for Merit, by any improvement of mens natural abilities. <hi>Qu. <hi>But do not the works of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, which follow Juſtification, deſerve eternal life, not from the Imputation of Christ's righteouſneſs, but from their own intrinſick worth, and proportionableneſs to the Reward, which is called the</hi>
                  </hi> Merit of condignity? <hi>Anſ.</hi> This were to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the whole contrivance of the Goſpel, which is a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial transferring our ſin, as a debt on Chriſt the Surety; and of his Righteouſneſſe and Merit, to be imputed to us, for our Juſtification, without any reſpect to works, and layeth down the very ſame way of life, which was in the Covenant of Works; as is clear, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5: 21. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not Heaven held forth is a Reward; ſo as our works do merit by bargain; and covenant?</hi> Mat. 20: 12. <hi>Anſ.</hi> No re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of debt can be found there, as that which is in ſtrick Juſtice due, but to ſhew, it is only of Grace, and no proportion betwixt that which is given, and their work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, We ſee theſe who came in at <hi>the laſt hour,</hi> had the ſame meaſure with them <hi>who had wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght all the day, Math.</hi> 20: 9. Nor can any Merit be in that claim, and reckoning: the greateſt labourer muſt ſtill ſay, when he hath done all that he can, <hi>That he is but an unprofitable ſervant, Luke</hi> 17: 10. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is it not promiſed,</hi> Rev. 3: 4. <hi>That ſome ſhall walk with Chreſt in white, becauſe they are worthy?</hi> Anſ.</hi> There it is clear, the Lord doth account them ſo, whom he hath accepted in his Son, and for whoſe ſake alone it is, 1 <hi>Cor. 4: 7. For who makes thee to differ from another? and what haſt thou, which thou haſt not received? then if tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> dideſt receive it, why doſt thou glory, as if thou hadst not received? <hi>Qu.</hi> Is there no neceſſity of works here, even in order to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know, 1. This is the way, in which God hath commanded us to walk, for our attaining Salvation. 2. Though they be not cauſes of our Juſtification, yet they are neceſſarily required in the ſubject, and perſon juſtified, as the inſeparable fruits of juſtifying Faith, by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105851:14"/> which, it is made evident to others, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2: 16. 3. They are of ſingular uſe, for a Chriſtians comfort and aſſurance. 4. They bring much honour to God, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15: 8. But it is ſure, nothing can be more clear, than the Doctrine of the reformed Church is, in aſſerting this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IF there be no humane Satisfaction and Merit, what ſafe adventuring can be on the overmeriting of ſome for others; and that Treaſure, in the Church of</hi> Romes <hi>hand, from the works of</hi> Superrogation, <hi>whereon their Abſolutions and Indulgences depend?</hi> Anſ.</hi> So horrid an Impoſture may let us ſee, what it is to be given up unto ſtrong delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: When it is ſo clear, 1. That the <hi>wiſe Virgins</hi> could ſpare no oyl out of their lamps to others, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25: 9. 2. That <hi>Every one muſt prove his own work, and bear his own burthen, Gal.</hi> 6: 6. 3. If we credit the fulneſſe of Chriſts Satisfaction, and its Infinite value, as the Scripture holds it forth, <hi>Heb. 10: 14. Who by one offering hath perfected for ever, thoſe who are ſanctified; and Heb. 7: 25. That he is able to ſave to the utmoſt;</hi> then no uſe can be alledged, for this ſupply of humane Satisfaction. 4. Let men but exerciſe Reaſon, and conſider, how this poſſibly can be known, that ſuch an <hi>overplus</hi> of Merit is ſure, or more than they need themſelves; and where any Rule can be found, which the Scripture never ſhewed, how to apply the ſame, or in whoſe hand this truſt is to be put. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of Chriſt only for the guilt of mortal ſins, and to free us from eternal puniſhment, but not of temporal? therefore we ſee a filling up of what is behind of the Sufferings of Chriſt for his body, which is the Church, Col.</hi>
                  </hi> 1: 24. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is clear, that Jeſus Chriſt made a perfect reconciliation for ſin, <hi>Dan. 9: 24. John.</hi> 1: 29. And no mite left for us to pay, by him, who anſwered the full price. 2. What the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle there ſhews, none can aver, was of Chriſts expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105851:14"/> ſufferings; but to ſhew that as his ſufferings were the price of our Redemption; ſo were they a ſeal and witneſs to the truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18: 37: In which reſpect the Saints alſo have their ſhare, in all following ages, to fill up the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt, in his body which is the Church, as a teſtimony to the Truth, which the great Witneſs himſelf did ſeal, and confirm with his Blood, who before <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate</hi> gave a good Confeſſion. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet may not this warrant ſuch plenary Indulgences, and Abſolutions of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, and a power to apply the Merit of others, which is ſo expreſs? Joh. 20: 23. Whoſe ſoever ſins ye remit, ſhall be remitted?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is a ſad commentary, deſtroying the Text, which here hath reſpect to Church-Cenſures, and is to ſhew what Authority, the Miniſters of Chriſt are cloathed with, and impowered by their Maſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to declare ſinners bound, or looſed from their ſins, according to the validity of that declarative ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, thus enſured, as they follow that rule for the ſame, in the exerciſe of Church Diſcipline; but not the leaſt ground is here, for ſuch plenary Indulgences they pretend, or to abſolve and relieve Souls out of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS there not clear ground for the Doctrine of Purgatory, whereon a great ſtreſs of many of the Romiſh principles vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly lyes, that though there be an acquittance from eternal death, for the truely penitent, yet is there a place after this life, where they muſt for a time be tormented, and ſuffer theſe pains of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, to expiate venial ſins, which their Prayers and Pennances here could not do?</hi> Anſ.</hi> The Scripture hath revealed no ſuch thing: but thence it is clear; 1. That ſin, by the Blood of Chriſt only can be expiated, and is his alone work, who <hi>hath purged our ſin himſelf, Heb.</hi> 1: 3. 2. That forgiveneſs from the Lord to thoſe who repent, is with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105851:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> no reſerve of venial ſins, or a temporal puniſhment for ſuch to ſatisfie juſtice, <hi>Ezeck. 18: 22. All his tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which hath committed, ſhall not be mentioned, Heb. 8: 12. I will be merciful to their unrighteouſneſſe, and their ſins, and iniquities, I will remember no more.</hi> 3. From the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we can know only a two fold ſtate of men, after this life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3: 36. And two wayes that accordingly lead thereto, <hi>Matth. 7: 14. Strait is the way that leadeth unto life, and the way to deſtruction broad.</hi> The Apoſtle ſheweth that no middle place is betwixt the Saints being vncloathed, and cloathed upon, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5: 1, 2. 5. The unconverted Theif found no Purgatory by the way, who had no Pennances, nor Church Indulgences, to lead him by the ſame, if the Infinite Merits of Chriſt were not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for all: In a word, this doth manifeſtly charge God with Injuſtice, as exacting double ſatisfaction for ſin, one from Chriſt, the other from the ſinner. <hi>Qu. <hi>But doth not the Apoſtle ſhew, there is a being ſaved, yet ſo as by fire? 1 Cor.</hi>
                  </hi> 3: 15. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Nothing can be more plain, if any read that Scripture, than that there is a figurative expreſſion, and the ſame with, <hi>verſe 13. The fire ſhall try every mans work;</hi> Which none can expound to be Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: but that not without temporal loſs, ſo as to have their work burned, theſe ſhall eſcape. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are not ſome venial ſins, which a temporal puniſhment may be ſufficient to expiat, and therefore ſuch paines do follow ſin here, as might evince a Purgatory after this?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is ſure, 1. <hi>That the wages of ſin is death, Rom:</hi> 6: 23. And no difference there is ſhewed betwixt venial and mortal. 2. If a full acquittance from the guilt, and puniſhment of ſin be by Jeſus Chriſt, and that he hath payed the whole price, no Satisfaction to Juſtice can be of uſe for temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 3. It is clear, the moſt ſharp chaſtiſements of the Saints in this life are for healing, and no effect of Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Juſtice, nor can give the laſt ground to plead for <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Satisfaction,</hi> or ſuch a thing as <hi>Purgatory</hi> after this life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105851:15"/>
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>BUt is there no Scripture warrant, for the Romiſh</hi> Maſs, <hi>as a real, external, Sacrifice propitiatory, for the living and the dead; and that wherein the body of Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally offered up?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is clear, 1. That not the leaſt footſtep of a Sacrifice, or of Chriſts offering his Body and Blood, was in the firſt inſtitution of the <hi>Euchariſt:</hi> nor in theſe Offices given to the Church, of <hi>Apoſtles, Paſtors, Teachers, &amp;c. Rom. 12: 6, 7, 8. 1 Cor.</hi> 12: 28. is there mention of any ſuch, as a ſacrificer of Chriſts Body. 2. No external Sacrifice can be now under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> theſe under the Law being only typical of that, which was accompliſhed in Jeſus Chriſt, who offered himſelf but once, <hi>Heb. 7: 27. And by this one offering hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified, Heb.</hi> 10: 18. So as this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the perfection of Chriſt's Offering, and his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſthood. 3. No ſacrifice can be propitiatory, which is without blood; ſince without that <hi>There is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, Heb</hi> 9: 22. 4. It is clear, in a true Sacrifice, the thing ſacrificed muſt be deſtroyed in the act of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing, which none dare ſay of the bleſſed Body of Chriſt; nor can it be conceived, how a repetition of the Offering up of Chriſt ſhould really be, and not of his Sufferings alſo. <hi>Qu. <hi>Can it be denyed, but ſome Offerings are even under the</hi> New Teſtament <hi>unto God?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know, in the Lords Supper there are Offerings of praiſe and love, with a ſolemn commemoration of Chriſt death, but no external Sacrifice there, or the leaſt ſhadow of ground from the Scripture for it. <hi>Qu. <hi>Did not</hi>
                  </hi> Mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hizedeck <hi>offer Bread and Wine, who was the Prieſt of the moſt High God? Gen.</hi> 14: 18. <hi>Anſ.</hi> His <hi>bringing it forth</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> is there ſhewed, but nothing to ſhew his <hi>Offering</hi> of it, or what could give ground for the Idolatrous ſervice of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> though on this they lay its greateſt weight. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105851:16"/> there not Prieſts now in times of the Goſpel, as under the Law?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We know One only eternal High Prieſt, who is ſuch as can have no ſucceſſour: and it is clear, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7: 26. that the Prieſt, and Offerer, under the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould be holy, undefiled, and ſeparate from ſinners,</hi> which I judge they dare not own: But what do they mean thereby, ſince it muſt either be to repeat over again Chriſts Sacrifice, which is impoſſible, and blaſphemous, or to preſent what was then done by him, which is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and no Sacrifice? yea even in this, are they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly divided, to give an account, wherein the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſacrificing conſiſts, whether in the words of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> or in putting it on the altar. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet may not ſome be preſent there with a ſafe Conſcience, when no evil is intended?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We ought not, from theſe grounds: 1. The ſcandal, and offend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is not to be judged from our intention, but from what is manifeſt to others, in our doing ſuch a thing. 2. The hardening of Papiſts in their way, this being a ſpecial ſymbol of their profeſſion, whereby they are diſcerned. 3. It were an obvious diſſimulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and with the adverſary, in that profeſſed communicating with them in an external part of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS it not an eſſential of the Chriſtian Religion, that ſuch a preciſe number of Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s is, and neither more nor fewer than Seven, as is the Doctrine of the Romiſh Church?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is indeed an eſſential of their Religion, but ſuch as could never ſhew its warrant from the <hi>Bible,</hi> where two <hi>Sacraments</hi> only can be found of Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> as having theſe requiſites to a Sacrament of the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> 1. An external viſible element. 2. That it be of expreſſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105851:16"/> inſtitution. 3. To have a promiſe of Grace and Pardon annexed thereto, which is not only ſignified, but offered and ſealed to all, who rightly partake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 4. That it be perpetual unto the Worlds end. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are theſe other five Sacraments of the Romiſh Church but of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention, to wit, Confirmation, Pennance, Extreme unction, Orders, and Marriage?</hi> Anſ.</hi> Since Divine Worſhip muſt be according to the Rule given us by the Lawgiver, it is clear, theſe have not the leaſt impreſs of a Divine appointment thereon. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is not Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion an ancient practice of the Church?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It was a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in the Primitive times, to bring Children Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and after they came to ſome years, before the Church, to put them in mind of their Baptiſm, and engagements they were under, which they now turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Sacrament, and therewith uſe Chriſm, which is Oyl mixed with Balm, putting it on the forehead, in the form of a Croſs, with theſe words; I ſign and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thee with the Chriſm of Salvation, giving them a blow on the face, with other fooliſh rites, by which they ſay the fulneſſe of the Holy Ghoſt is given: But how this is a Sacrament, or by what Inſtitution ordained, or what promiſe of Grace and Pardon is annexed hereto, muſt be ſought elſewhere, than from the <hi>Bible. <hi>Qu.</hi> But is not Penances a part of Repentance, and a viſible ſign thereof? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> The publick profeſſion of Repentance, for publick ſcandalous ſins, is a duty; but no ſuch outward ſign was ever inſtituted in the Word, as Whipping, Pilgrimage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, nothing more contrary thereto, than their declared meaning of this to be a Satisfaction to juſtice, and Compenſation of the wrong done unto God thereby; nor can they agree among themſelves about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentality thereof, if the form be in the act of the Prieſts Abſolution, or not. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are not Marriage and Orders unqueſtionably of Divine appointment.</hi> Anſ.</hi> None will deny that <hi>Marriage,</hi> and theſe Offices appointed by Chriſt in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105851:17"/> his houſe, have their Warrant in the Scripture; but not as Sacraments; yea is it not amazing, how the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> ſhould aſſert this, who maintain the uſe of theſe Sacraments to be neceſſary to Salvation, when all of their Church are by their own Doctrine excluded from one of them, the whole Laity from Orders, and the Clergy from Marriage. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is there not yet ground for extreme Unction,</hi> Jam. 4: 14. <hi>In which with the Oyl of Olive they anoint divers parts of the bodies of thoſe; who are in death bed, with ſuch words; I anoint ſuch a place, that wherein thou haſt ſinned, thou mayeſt be forgiven?</hi> Anſ.</hi> For what the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle there mentions: 1. The recovery of the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is evidently intended; but this extreme Unction in not uſed, until the recovery of the party be paſt hope. 2. The health there promiſed was miraculous, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that time, when the Faith of Miracles was in the Church; and temporary, for ſuch as had the extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie gift of healing: but for the Elders of the Church praying over the Sick, though not having ſuch a gift now, we deny not its prepetual uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>HAth not that Article of the Romiſh Doctrine,</hi>
                  </hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, <hi>clear warrant in the Scripture, that Chriſts bodily preſence in the Sacrament, is ſuch, as the whole ſubſtance of the Bread and Wine there, in the act of Conſecration, is turned into the ſubſtance of his Body and Blood? <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  </hi> It is manifeſt, 1. That it could be no more a Sacrament, if the ſign ſhould be turned into the thing ſignified. 2. It is expreſly to deny the real Body of Chriſt, and that he did viſibly and locally leave this World; <hi>Whom the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens must contain, until the time of the reſtitution of all things, Acts</hi> 3: 11. 3. It is moſt directly contrarie to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where it is ſo evident, that the Bread and Wine remain ſtill the ſame, after the Conſecration, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105851:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>verſ. 26. So oft you eat of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> this Bread:</hi> And <hi>let a Man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of this Bread, 1 Cor. 10: 16. The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Christ?</hi> Yea, <hi>Acts</hi> 2: 46. Where the partaking of the Sacrament is called the <hi>Breaking of Bread,</hi> in all which it is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſhewed to be ſtill <hi>Bread.</hi> 4. It is clear, that Jeſus Chriſt as Man, cannot be in divers places at once; nor his Body at the ſame time in Heaven, and upon Earth in the Hoſt, being <hi>made like unto us in all things, ſin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, Heb.</hi> 2: 17. 5. This is to ſubject the bleſſed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, now in a glorified ſtate, to the greateſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominies, ſuch as to go into the belly, to be eaten by his enemies; to be deſtroyed by rats and other beaſts, the verie conceiving of which ſhould cauſe horrour. <hi>Qu. <hi>Are not theſe the very words of Inſtitution, when Jeſus Chriſt took the Bread, This is my Body?</hi> Anſ.</hi> They are, but nothing more uſual in Scripture, than ſuch figurative ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as this is, to ſhew the ſacramental Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Bread and Chriſts Body, as 1 <hi>Cor. 10: 1. The Rock was Chriſt. Joh. 15: 1. I am the true vine;</hi> which I am ſure none can take in the literal ſenſe: But I confeſſe, ſuch need not fear to loſe their cauſe, who from the Church's Authority can make void Scripture, Senſe, and Reaſon at once. <hi>Qu. <hi>Wherein doth this contradict Senſe, or Reaſon.</hi> Anſ.</hi> It expreſly ſhews, 1. That we muſt not credit our own eyes, and that all who were witneſſes of the Miracles of Chriſt, could have no certainty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by their ſight; though theſe were given to confirm the Truth unto mens ſenſes. 2. That the accidents of Bread and Wine, ſuch as colour, taſte, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> can remain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Subject. 3. That the ſame numerical Body ſhould be in ſo many places at once, which is in effect, to deny the Body of Chriſt to be humane and finite. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet is it not agreeable to take away the Cup from the People, in the Eucharist?</hi> Anſ.</hi> If the written Word have any weight, it is then ſure, how contrarie this is, 1. To the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105851:18"/> and Command of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26: 27. Which in theſe words is expreſſe, <hi>Drink ye all of it.</hi> 2. To the Command, and Rule given us by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 11: 23. Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup,</hi> which hath there a reſpect to all, who have cauſe for ſelf examination. 3. Doth ſo far fruſtrate that end of the appointment of the Lords Supper, for commemorating his death and ſufferings, <hi>So oft as you eat of this bread, and drink of this cup, ye ſhew forth the Lords death, till he come again:</hi> ſince it is clear, they cannot aright celebrate the memory thereof, who partake not of that part of the Sacrament, whereby we comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate the effuſion of Chriſt's blood. 4. Though in the firſt adminiſtration, by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers then were Apoſtles; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et is it manifeſt, he did then enter the whole Chriſtian Church in poſſeſſion of ſuch a priviledge, in that very man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er he gave it, and not the leaſt ſhadow for this reſtriction to be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>IS there not ſafe Worſhipping God, under a viſible repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, and in an Image, according to the practice of the Romiſh Church?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is not their practice only; but profeſſed Doctrine and Principle, that the Images of the Trinity are not for a ſhew ſet up, but for Religious adoration; which, 1. Is a moſt direct violation of the moral Law: <hi>Deut. 5: 8. Thou ſhall not make unto thy ſelf any graven Image, or the ſimilitude of any thing, to bow down to it.</hi> 2. It is to change the glory of the inviſible God, <hi>into the likeneſſe of a ſinful creature, Rom.</hi> 1: 23. Which none can deny to be the groſſeſt Idolatry. 3. It is a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe breach of the Command, which forbids all ſerving the true God, after the manner which the Heathens uſed in ſerving their Idols, <hi>Deut. 12: 30, 31. Take heed to thy ſelf, that thou be not ſnared, by asking how theſe Nations did ſerve
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105851:18"/> their Gods, thou ſhalt not do ſo to the Lord thy God;</hi> which is not, thou ſhalt not do ſo to theſe Idols, but not in that manner to the true God, as they did to their Idols. 4. There can be no poſſible repreſenting the Inviſible God, by any outward reſemblance: <hi>To whom will ye liken me? Iſa.</hi> 46: 5. And therefore, when the Law was given, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4: 12. The People <hi>Heard a voice, but ſaw no ſhape,</hi> leſt thereby they ſhould take occaſion to repreſent him by an external image. 5. How great a ſin it is to conceive, or imagine in our hearts, that the glorious God is like any thing, how excellent ſoever, We think, it is clear, <hi>Acts</hi> 17: 29. <hi>Qu. <hi>But can this charge the Romiſh Church with Idolatry. ſince they do not fix or terminate their Worſhip on the Image, but on what is thus repreſented?</hi> Anſ.</hi> No ſubtil diſtinction will acquit before the Lord, and at the bar of his Word, what he hath ſo expreſly condemned; when it is clear, 1. That not only worſhipping with our mind the Image, but all corporal adoration thereof is forbidden, as Idolatrous worſhip, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down thereto.</hi> 2. None will deny but <hi>Aarons calf,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Jeroboams,</hi> were intended for the true God; yet their worſhip was moſt groſſe Idolatrie. 3. We find the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent, though an inſtituted type, under the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> taken down and deſtroyed, when once the People begun in an Idolatrous way, to look after it. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is it not lawful to make an Image of Chriſt, who is truly Man, for keeping up the remembrance of him in our Worſhip?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We may not, 1. Becauſe it is expreſlie forbidden to frame unto ourſelves the likeneſſe of any thing in Heaven, where the bleſſed body of Chriſt now is. 2. Since both natures in him are inſeparable, this were to fix a repreſentation in our mind of his manhood only. dividing it from his Divinity; and thus give a manifeſt advantage to Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm. 3. Nothing from the Scripture giveth the leaſt ſhew of any ſhape, or lineament of his Body, to let us ſee, that under no viſible Image, we ſhould ſeek to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105851:19"/> him. 4. The true portraicture of Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, we have ſet before our eyes in the Goſpel, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, as is clear, <hi>Gal. 3: verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet is there not ſafe ground, for the worſhip of Angels, of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and of the Saints; ſince this is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected unto them, as unto God, but in a lower degree?</hi> Anſ.</hi> God alone is. and ought to be the object of Religious Worſhip, which in no degree can be given unto any creature whatſoever, as is expreſſe from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>Matth. 4: 10. Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> 2. All worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels is forbidden; <hi>Col. 2: 18. Rev.</hi> 10: 10. 3. Since Religious Worſhip is due to God alone, we may in no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree give it to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or the Saints, ſince there is <hi>but one Mediator Jeſus Chriſt, 1 Tim.</hi> 2: 5. Yea this were, ſo far, to put them in the place of God, to provoke his jealouſie, <hi>Exo. 24: 14. Thou ſhalt worſhip no other God, for the Lord, whoſe Name is Jealous, is a Iealous God:</hi> And of this is he in a ſpecial way Jealous, that none be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partners with him in his Worſhip. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is there no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable uſe of Images?</hi> Anſ.</hi> The uſe of Images is not ſimply condemned, for we find ſome in the Temple by expreſſe Command, though they were only Typical, to ſhadow out things to be fulfilled under the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> there is a Political uſe of Images alſo lawful for ornament, and to keep up the remembrance of friends; ſome hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical and for doctrinal uſe: but none ſhould be ſet up in Churches, or in the leaſt ſet apart for Religious Worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>MAy not the Worſhip of God, in the publick Prayers of the Church be in an unknown tongue, according to the Popiſh Doctrine?</hi> Anſ.</hi> You have the Apoſtles anſwer to this, 1 <hi>Cor. 14: 2. He that ſpeaketh in an unknown tongue, ſpeaketh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105851:19"/> not unto men, but unto God; for who underſtands him?</hi> In which he ſhews, there can be no viſible communion, in ſuch an act of worſhip: and lets us ſee, how it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts one great end of publick worſhip, that ſuch can have no real and heart conſenting therein, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſiby called for in that dutie of publick Prayer; as we ſee, verſ. 16. <hi>For how ſhall be that occupieth the room of the unlearned, ſay Amen, at thy giving of thanks, ſince he underſtands not what thou ſayest?</hi> Qu. <hi>Is it not enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt Church-guides with this, to whom the People makes their Confeſſion?</hi> Anſ. We know no ſuch implicite relyance taught by the Scripture; but there is no cure, where men will intruſt both Religion, and Reaſon at once, to the diſpoſal of others. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet is there not a neceſſity of ſome Implicite relyance on theſe, ſince according to the Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, none can be aſſured of his own Salvation, but what he hath on the aſſurance of his Prieſt and Confeſſor.</hi> Anſ.</hi> Nothing is more clear, than a Chriſtians acceſſe to be aſſured of his being in the ſtate of Grace, and that he hath paſſed from death to life, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3: 14. Upon theſe grounds, 1. Becauſe <hi>a rejoycing in the hope of the glory of God,</hi> is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable here, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, <hi>Rom. 5: verſ.</hi> 2. 2. That by the works and evidences of Sanctification, a moſt firm and infallible aſſurance, is in this life given to the Saints, 1 <hi>Ioh, 3: 18, 19. Let us not love in tongue neither in word, but in deed and truth; and hereby do we know, that we are in the truth, and ſhall aſſure our hearts before him.</hi> 3. By the teſtimonie of the Spirit, witneſſing with our Spirits, <hi>That we are the children of God, Rom</hi> 8: 16. 4. By that earneſt of the Spirit in our hearts, <hi>whereby we are ſealed unto the day of Redemption, Eph. 1: 13, 14. &amp;</hi> 4: 30. <hi>Qu. <hi>Is there no ground for that Article of the Romiſh Doctrine, that under pain of damnation, there be a Confeſſion of the most ſecret ſins of men, yea, their very thoughts, ſo far as they can remember, unto the Prieſt, according to that,</hi> James 5: 16. <hi>Confeſſe your faults one to another?</hi> Anſ.</hi> We ſee as much ground from this,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105851:20"/> to confeſſe to the people, as to the Prieſt; nor doth the Scripture warrant any ſuch thing; but this aſſurance have we, that <hi>He who confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſins ſhall find mercy, Prov.</hi> 28: 13. Which none will deny is there meant unto God: nor did the Saints in Scripture know Auricular Confeſſion. I <hi>ſaid, I will confeſſe my tranſgreſſions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin, Pſal.</hi> 32: 5. Though we deny not the duty of publick Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in the caſe of publick and ſcandalous ſins; but if men ſhut not their eyes; nothing but a politick intereſt is here, to be thus on the moſt hid, and cloſe counſels of men, by ſuch a pretext to keep the Conſcience under awe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. <hi>BUt how ſhould that plea be anſwered, which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church hath to prove their Religion, from its uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, univerſality, and an uninterrupted ſucceſſion?</hi> Anſ.</hi> It is I confeſſe ſtrange and aſtoniſhing; when ſo clear, 1. For her <hi>Unity,</hi> That beſides what known differences they are at amongſt themſelves, in many Doctrines, they are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly divided about the very foundation of their Faith, and <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their Church, whether it reſolve on the Pope alone, or on the Pope and a Council, or that late found-out Rule of <hi>Oral Tradition.</hi> 2. For an <hi>Univerſality,</hi> it is eaſie to know, how much more than the one half, where the Chriſtian Faith is embraced through the World, doth not at all own the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> And 3. For that <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of their Church, and unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted line of <hi>Popes,</hi> they will not themſelves debate, how there have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree <hi>Popes</hi> at one time, yea by what horrid means ſome of them got up to that throne, as their greateſt Writers are forced to confeſſe. <hi>Qu. <hi>But is the Apoſtacy of that Church ſuch, as there is no ſafe union with it, nor hope of being ſaved in their Religion?</hi> Anſ.</hi> If <hi>Rome</hi> be that ſpiritual <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 18: 4. as is there moſt evident, then is the command peremptorie, <hi>to come out of her, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105851:20"/> being partakers of her ſins, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y be partakers of her plagues:</hi> yea ſuch a threatning we may read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14: 9, 10. as ſhould cauſe men to tremble, who are not under a ſtrange height of induration; and now ſince the breaking up of ſo great a light, and theſe clear diſcoveries of the truth, are the <hi>Waters become bloody, Revel.</hi> 16: 3. <hi>Qu. <hi>Yet can all this make out the charge of Antichriſtianiſm, or that the Pope is the Antichriſt, who is ſo expreſly foretold, 2 Theſ. 2: 3, 4?</hi> Anſ.</hi> To reſolve ſuch a thing, theſe are undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly clear, 1. That the Holy Ghoſt, in the Scripture, hath been in a more than ordinary way, particular, in point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Antichriſt out, by ſuch notorious marks and chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, that after ages might know him, if they will not ſhut their eyes; and that a moſt exact portraicture is there drawn of ſuch an adverſarie, what ſhould be his form and ſhape, with the manner of his appearance. 2. Except we deny our Senſes, it is certain, that we ſee with our eyes ſuch an one, as is there ſhewed forth; ſo as none ever knew the face of a Man, by his Picture drawn to the life in a frame, better then the Church this day may know Antichriſt, and that this is he, who ſo clearlie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers all theſe marks, which in the Scripture are given of him; even he, <hi>Whoſe coming ſhall be after the working of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, with all power, ſigns, and lying wonders, forbidding to marry, and commanding to abſtain from meats, which God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be uſed with thanksgiving; who ſitteth in the Temple of God and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witcheth the Kings of the earth with his inchantments, and is drunk with the blood of the martyrs of Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> yea, whoſe Traffick, and Merchandice, is not onlie Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but <hi>The ſouls of men, Rev.</hi> 18: 13. And can we be in the dark, to know or diſcover who this Antichriſt is, whoſe Doctrine is ſtated in ſo direct an oppoſition to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and the great deſign of the Goſpel. 3. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt muſt be already come, and revealed, elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, that Prophecy can never have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105851:21"/> its accompliſhment, ſince even in the Apoſtles times, this <hi>Myſtery began to worke,</hi> and he who <hi>for a time did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> his coming, the <hi>Heathen Empire of Rome,</hi> hath been long ſince taken out of the way; and as the Scripture points his firſt coming, and appearance in the firſt times of the Church; ſo his laſt cloſe, and final ruine to be near the <hi>ſecond coming of the Lord</hi> 4. It is thus undeniable, that this adverſarie can be no ſingle perſon, or of a ſhort continuance, but is a politick Bodie and Kingdom, centred, and united in one ſupream Head, and with a ſucceſſion for many ages. 5. It is clear, that theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Marks and Characters given by the Scripture, for the Churches knowing of Antichriſt, could anſwer to no Adverſarie elſe, which Jeſus Chriſt ever had under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> either Pagan or Mahumetan. <hi>Qu. <hi>Since Antichrists fall muſt be by the Word, as is clear,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2: 4. <hi>whom the Lord ſhall conſume by the breath of his mouth, can it be now applicable to the Romiſh Church, whilſt Popery is ſo ſpreading, even in thoſe Parts, where the Word is most power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached?</hi> Anſ.</hi> This needs not be ſtrange, if we conſider, 1. That Antichriſts fall, according to the Scripture, muſt be by degrees, as his riſe was. 2. That where the truth is not <hi>received in love, 2 Theſ.</hi> 2: 18. it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long want judicial effects, to be given up to ſtrong deluſions. 3. It is eaſie to ſee, how ſuch as at this day have fallen off to Poperie, are not upon debate, or by arguments to their judgement engaged, but it is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible product of a licentious time, and from an unuſual growth of Atheiſm and Ignorance; yea thoſe only are found to change their Religion, who never in earneſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced any. 4. Yet can none deny thoſe great and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie effects, the preached word hath had to recover the Church from <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> darkneſſe, in theſe laſt ages, to which thoſe famous Plantations of the Goſpel, in <hi>Britain, Ireland, France, Germany,</hi> the <hi>Low countries,</hi> &amp;c. are to this day a witneſſe, where the greateſt Atheiſts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105851:21"/> may ſee an immediate appearance of God, and ſomething above nature, with that convincing increaſe of light, as enforceth ſuch even to gnaw their tongue with pain, who do nor ceaſe to oppoſe the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="considerations">
               <head>Some ſerious Conſiderations further anent Popery, and the import of that great controverſie betwixt the Romish, and reformed Churches at this day.</head>
               <p>THough there ſeems ſmall grounds of hope, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſuch, who in the holy judgement of God, are given up to that ſtrong deluſion of Popery, and ceaſeth not to oppoſe themſelves to the cleareſt diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the truth: yet this being ſo ſad and deplorable a ſight, to ſee how much of the Chriſtian World thus Periſh, who will not once open their eyes, and is ſo clear, that under the greateſt of judgements, this way muſt involve them, (if the Scripture of God have any weight or credit with ſuch:) yea ſince this is ſo grave and concerning a duty, now in theſe laſt times, to bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt Antichriſt, and purſue without ceaſing that call, whatever ſucceſs it ſhould have, that men would come out of Babylon, and haſten from under approaching wrath and judgment: I ſhall here add, to what is premitted before upon this ſubject, ſome ſerious <hi>Conſiderations</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Popery,</hi> with an appeale to the Conſcience of the Adverſary, yea to their reaſon and judgment, if they will allow its free exerciſe herein, anent the truth thereof.</p>
               <div n="1" type="consideration">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105851:22"/>
                  <head>CONSID. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIrſt,</hi> At what a rate by clear and undeniable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, from the Romiſh Doctrine and principles, one can be Popiſh, conforme to their way; and what is neceſſarily imported in being a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> as they thus terme themſelves, which is not more ſtrange, and aſtoniſhing in it ſelf, than may be clear in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it is to deliver up their reaſon and judgment to the conduct of ſuch, of whom they muſt ſee true cauſe to feare, adventuring upon in the ſmalleſt of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward intereſts: And where it is ſo viſible, its <hi>money</hi> for <hi>merite,</hi> and that all can be ſold at this market upon ſuch a price; yea where the poore only muſt be left hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, who thus hath not to expiate their guilt, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſs a plenary indulgence: as <hi>Petrarch</hi> of old was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to ſay, that if <hi>Judas</hi> could come with the price of his Maſters blood to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> market, he might be welcome to buy an abſolution; where, no ſin needs want a diſpenſation to allow it, or a pardon for its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment, if their purſe can poſſibly anſwere thereto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This is to quite that judgment of diſcerning given them of God, and be ſhut out of all Proper knowledge of the Scripture with their own conſent (except theſe of the Clergy) ſo as they muſt not truſt their own eyes, but others in the great intereſt of their eternal ſtate, and thus take the Romiſh Authority for their Bible; yea ſuch, whom they cannot but ſee, what Palpable ignorance in ſome, and deceit and falſhood is in others of thoſe they thus implicitely credit, and that the concernes of this earth, and their private intereſt doth for the moſt of ſuch more ſway, than any thing of Religion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is by cleareſt conſequence manifeſt, that this is a viſible betaking of themſelves to a Covenant of Works,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105851:22"/> and to ſtand thereby, in the moſt expreſs oppoſition to the great intent of the Goſpel; ſince according to their Principles, it is <hi>merite,</hi> yea their own Proper merite muſt be the way for their obtaining of heaven; and all they aſcribe to Jeſus Chriſt herein is this, only to give life and Salvation to their merites, which yet are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and from their own intrinſick worth, without the imputation of Chriſts merite thereto, thus merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; as they terme it, <hi>ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ondigno:</hi> And thus only do they admit, a reſtoring again by him of a Covenant of Works on the ſame termes with the firſt; <hi>Do this and live.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It muſt be at that rate, one can be this day Popiſh, of the groſſeſt Idolatry, and a <hi>turning the glory of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God, into the ſimilitude of a corruptible man,</hi> Rom. 1: verſ. 23. with a moſt expreſs counteracting of that great precept of the Moral Law againſt bowing down and Worſhipping of any graven Image, they being no leſs thus guiltie of an Idolatrous Worſhip, than either the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of Old, or the Pagan world could be charged with; ſince both had a reſpect further than the Image it ſelf, the one to the true God, and the other to their feigned Deity.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. What ever liberty this way gives to ſin, and to lay the ſtreſs of their inward peace on the Prieſts abſolution; yet it is clear, that at that rate on theſe tearmes can one be <hi>Popiſh</hi> this day, to ſubject themſelves to a yoke and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage from men, that without a judicial ſtroke on their Conſcience might ſeeme intolerable; ſuch as <hi>Auricular Confeſſion</hi> to a Prieſt, of their moſt ſecret ſins, and this under the pain of damnation; their <hi>Pennan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es,</hi> with that blind and unlimited obedience therein to their Church Guids without acceſs to conſult the Scripture; as if this way of expiating ſin could be a Satisfaction before the holy God, ſuch as their whipping of themſelves, and going in Pilgrimage to ſome Superſtitious place, yea thus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105851:23"/> becauſe they be grievous to the fleſh; but why not rather, an offering up of the fruit of their body for the ſin of their ſoul, as thoſe of old unto Molech, which might witneſs a further degree of doing violence to their own fleſh. If men might thus think by a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of their deviſing to appeaſe the Juſtice of God.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. This neceſſarily alſo muſt follow an embracement of <hi>Popery,</hi> and ſubjecting to that way; to be put beyond a poſſibility of any inward peace here, or quiet as to their future ſtate in another world, ſince it is undeniable. 1. They muſt have ſome merite of their own, and an humane Satisfaction to confide in, and on that foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of good works, lay the weight of obtaining life, whilſt ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> according to their own Principles they ſee, there is no poſſible being ſure, if theſe ſhall be found equivalent in value to anſwere this end. 2. That no aſſurance of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is ſo much as attaineable, according to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. 3. How ſad a cure, as have no ſuteableneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to eaſe a diſquiet and awakened Conſcience, does their Principles bring, ſuch as <hi>Pennances, their own Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, the Pop's Pardon,</hi> or <hi>abſolution of the Prieſt, invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints and Images,</hi> whence it was in the darkneſs of <hi>Popery,</hi> moſt found themſelves under that inforcement for ſo many dotations, and to ſtretch their ſtate to the furtheſt for <hi>ſoul-maſſes,</hi> ſince they could find no ground for their ſouls quiet here. 4. And does not this way and Doctrine moſt viſibly purſue men, not unto death on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but beyond it, through theſe tormenting thoughts and fear of a <hi>Purgatory</hi> to come, and that uncertainty as to the time or terme of releaſe, ſo as at the beſt, death muſt have a terrible and affrighting look.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. If men would bring this near their thoughts, no leſs can ſerve to be a <hi>Popiſh proſelyte</hi> than a manifeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volvement in the blood of all the Saints, which hath been ſhed, and ſerving themſelves Heir to both the guilt and judgment of ſuch horrid and unexpreſſible cruelty
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105851:23"/> exerced by the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> on thoſe for ſo many ages paſt, who through grace did reſiſt unto the death, ſtriving for the truth againſt Antichriſtianiſme: for it is clear, how ſuch comes on the ſame ſcore by their virtual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and juſtifying the ſame with as real acceſſion before the Lord thereunto, as though they had actually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred. Oh what a reckoning will this once be found, to enter into eternity with, before the judgment ſeat of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p n="8">8, And is it now poſſible for any to be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> but at that rate of reſiſting the cleareſt diſcoveries of the truth, and an expreſs doing deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to be cured, and to come to the light, now when <hi>Antichriſtianiſme</hi> is by ſuch undeniable evidences reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the world, as men cannot be in the dark, who this great Adverſary is, that does not ſhut their own eyes from it. Oh! what a revenge does hatred and malice at the truth, cauſe, that can turn men cruel againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nor is that ſtroke of judicial blindneſs more ſtrange and amazeing this day on the <hi>Jewes,</hi> when ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with ſo clear diſcoveries of the truth, than this now may be, which is upon the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee that deſperat ſtate they are in, when ſuch undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able light is held out from the Scriptures there anent, nay, it muſt be ſaid, who will not ſee this?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. I muſt here further add, how evident alſo this is to be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and enrolled with ſuch a party, that it is no leſs, than to ſtand under that moſt dreadful peremptory threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as is in the whole of the Bible denounced againſt ſuch, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> theſe times of light ſhall engage with that way, Rev. 14: 9. <hi>If any man Worſhip the beaſt and his Image, and receive his mark in his fore head, or in his hand, the ſame ſhall drink of the wine of the wrath of God, which is powred out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture, into the cup of his indignation, and he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and in preſence of the Lamb, and the ſmoak of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105851:24"/> aſcendeth up for ever and ever, and they have no rest day nor night, who worſhip the beaſt and his imag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and who ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth the mark of his name.</hi> Oh! If men would be ſo far awakned with the dread of this threatning, as once to come and ſee but with their own eyes, to what party this is applicable, and expreſly pointed at by the Spirit of God there: and it is ſure they could not then be in the dark, how deep it drawes, under what pretext ſo ever, for any to be <hi>Popiſh.</hi> Nor is it ſtrange, that after ſuch abuſed light, hell becometh now more hot and more inevitable than before, whilſt ſo much of the Chriſtian World (who own that name and Profeſſion) do ſhut their eyes and ears at ſo clear and diſtinct a ſound from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſeemes to roll over all certainty hereof, to the deciſion and irrevocable Sentence of the Great Judge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="consideration">
                  <head>CONSID. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SEcondly,</hi> Can it be in the dark this day, if this be not upon Choice, that the great intereſt of the Reformed Church in contending againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> is a moſt expreſs appearance, and contending for the Truth of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Doctrine of the Scripture delivered to us in the Old and New Teſtament, And is ſo diſcernable upon theſe great Heads. 1. That there is but one Mediator betwixt God and Sinners, againſt ſuch direct oppoſition thereto in the Doctrine of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> that brings in a plurality of Mediators, and the Worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints departed, for that end. 2. In behalf of the reality of Chriſts humane nature, which by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> is ſubjected to have a new created being in their conſecrated <hi>Hoſtia,</hi> at each time, &amp; every where, at the pleaſure of a wretched man; which is in effect a moſt expreſs denying of his bleſſed body to be humane and finite. 3. It is clear, how expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned the Proteſtant Church is, in oppoſition to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105851:24"/> to contend for the reality of Chriſts death and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for his Elect. And that this time is come and paſt, no more poſſibly to be repeated again, wherein he <hi>once appeared in the end of the world to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, Heb. 9: 26. And by one offering hath for ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected them that are ſanctified, Heb.</hi> 10: 14. Againſt that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid blaſphemy of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> which they own as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated offering of the bleſſed body of the Redeemer, by the hands of the Prieſt unto God, as a Propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the living and the dead, which is ſo evident a ſubverting the foundations of Chriſtianity, and to make void the infinite value and efficacy of the death and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt once offered, and for ever in behalf of his Elect, whilſt they thus own a continued offering of his body, which as the Apoſtle ſhewes, Heb. 9: 25. that if Chriſt had offered himſelf often, he behoved to have fuffered often. 4. And is it not clear, that great inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of truth, the Reformed Church is now preſſed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon, againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> is the Doctrine of Chriſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us in the Scripture, as that whereon we muſt found and reſolve our faith, and not the Authority of men, which they ſo expreſly oppoſe and deny; ſo as it is no leſs than the Chriſtian cauſe and quarrel, for which all who loves the truth, are called to contend, and that we ſhould not be bereſt of that bleſſed infallible rule and ſtandart of truth, by thoſe, whoſe great aime is, to have it denuded of all Authority, but what is precarious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on them: nor to be ſo much as intelligible, and to have an articular voice, until they cauſe it ſpeak, and put what ſenſe thereon they pleaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="consideration">
                  <head>CONSID. III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THirdly,</hi> It may be aſtoniſhing (and is ſurely one of the greateſt depths of the Judgment of God this day) to ſee what of the world, with their own conſent, is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105851:25"/> ſubjected to ſo viſible, and notour an <hi>impoſture,</hi> as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is, whilſt ſuch, as it would ſeeme not conceivea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, how men can exerce reaſon, and not as in a deep ſleep, and have this hid from their eyes, the obvious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and impoſture of ſuch a way, where no Religion but a compound of humane Policy, with their own private intereſt and gain, is wholly intended. About which, I ſhall offer, (I hope I may with ſome confidence ſay, it's for the truths ſake) a ſhort touch here at, in ſome undeniable juſtances.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. None will debate how this way is framed for ſuch an intereſt, that there may be a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aunt and allowance from the <hi>Pope</hi> for any ſin, and to tranſgreſs the expreſs Lawes of the great Lawgiver, yea this put to ſale; Oh what a ſtrange device, that for money men may have a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to deſtroy themſelves: Whilſt on the other hand, nothing is followed with more ſevere threatnings, then an abſolute ſubjecting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o their arbitrary Commands, ſo that one may ſafely diſobey the holy God, and this with a warrant; but not the Pope, and his Clergy under the hazard of condemuation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That ſuch a ſtock and treaſure of merites ſhould be in keeping by the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> and under their truſt to diſpoſe of, as a thing depoſited into their hand by ſuch, who had more than enough for themſelves to ſerve for the uſe of others? And thus at their diſpoſal to give out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to ſatisfy divine Juſtice for thoſe, who have not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient merite of their own; this only being neceſſarily provided, that theſe who get a ſhare of ſuch a treaſure, compenſe it by ſomewhat equiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lent, and buy it ere they have it: but herein could they never reſolve the world how to be ſure, if theſe merites were truely more than ſuch, whoſe they were, needed themſelves, or how they came into their hand, or was intruſted by them to apply; or if their ſtrength be not long ſince ſpent and exhauſted by ſo long continued application in ſuch innumerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105851:25"/> given out of that treaſury: Oh! what a deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable contrivance is here, which I confeſs, ſhould be owned as one of the greateſt Maſter pieces of cheatry, as ever the world knew; if it were only to cheat men of their purſe, but this goes further, to thoſe great intereſts, of the immortal ſoul; and yet ſo many will not ſee the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intent of this trade and merchandice, that it is indeed the merchandice of the ſouls of men, ſo expreſly foretold by the holy Ghoſt, Rev. 18: 13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Their taking on them to change the condition of the dead, and enſure to their friends the happy eſtate of their ſoul upon ſome large offerings to the Church for this. As likewiſe that reſpect and veneration they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire from men to the reliques of the Saints deceaſed, whereto they aſcribe ſuch power both againſt fin, and for healing diſeaſes of the body: yea moſt of theſe pretended reliques, ſuch as muſt neceſſarily plead ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary miracle to be wrought for their continued preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that thus they may with confidence perſwade the world, their having ſome bone or ſcull of the Apoſtles &amp; Primitive Saincts to be ſtill ſeen, if any have a heart to give a price for it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Romiſh Pope</hi> is the true Succeſſor of <hi>Peter,</hi> and thus Chriſts Vicar as they tearme him, upon the earth which men muſt needs take upon truſt, with an impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite, faith from ſuch, whoſe preferment, and gain in the World ſhould be other wiſe ruined, if this be not taken off their hand, whilſt yet it is ſo undeniable, at what a ſtrait they are, to put a handſome ſhape on this device, or how the World can know upon any ſure gronud. 1. How <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome,</hi> or that he was ſetled in a peculiar manner Biſhop in that See, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, nor the moſt ancient records of the Church gives the leaſt ſhadow of ground for. 2, How the <hi>Pope</hi> becometh his Succeſſor, or upon what warrant, yea, that this ſhould be an Article of mens faith, where
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105851:26"/> the Scripture is wholly ſilent. 3. How that pretended ſucceſſion to <hi>Peter</hi> in that particular Dioceſs of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould have a Catholick Power and Headſhip over the whole Church annexed thereto, ſo as all who ſucceed in in the one, muſt alſo in the other. 4. How a warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Succeſſion of each particular <hi>Pope;</hi> can be made ſure to the Apoſtle, upon this pretended right, and that he hath lawfully ſucceeded; ſince if this be nul, and the election be unlawful, they have then with their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent no promiſe of Aſſiſtance, nor obedience in this caſe due. 5. When it is ſo clear, that the Power of the Keyes were given no leſs to the reſt of the Apoſtles, then to <hi>Peter,</hi> as is expreſs <hi>Matth.</hi> 18: 18, 19. yea, that <hi>Peter</hi> claimed no ſuch preſidence amongſt the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as may be ſeen <hi>Act.</hi> 15. upon what ground can they thus refound ſo great a claime as this? Oh what an amazing infatuation are thoſe in, who ſhould take this upon truſt, the very recital whereof is ſo obvious a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of it ſelf: And that on ſuch a pretended Power and Supremacy of <hi>Peter,</hi> the whole weight and ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture <hi>of the Romiſh Hierarchy</hi> muſt leane, yea which is of a higher concerne, that on this, by undeniable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, muſt be rolled over a weight no leſs, than the eternal intereſt, and periſhing of many millions of ſouls. who upon this Plenary Power and Infallibility of the <hi>Pope,</hi> thus founded upon ſuch a ground, do adventure with ſuch an Acquittance and Abſolution, as their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into another World.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That notable device of <hi>Purgatory</hi> may be a convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing witneſs to the horrid impoſture of <hi>Popery,</hi> than which nothing could have been more ſubſervient to that great deſigne of a lucrative intereſt, and to keep the people under a continued aw and terror; yea what improvement for ſo many ages they have made of this for their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate gain, that it may be ſeen, the Romiſh Church ſhould loſe one of the greateſt revenues it hath, if purgatory
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105851:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> were not kept up amongſt them, &amp; is beyond reckoning by themſelves what continued income this hath had, <hi>&amp; quantum haec fabula profuit Romanae Eccleſiae.</hi> But Oh! ſuch as will thus adventure hereon, may have ſaddeſt cauſe to feare, that this Purgatory, on their immediat parting with time, be found a real hell, whence no releaſe, or Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity thereof can be, though all the treaſures of the earth could be given for the ſame; and then ſhall know this ſad verification of this truth 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2: 11, 12. Which ſo expreſly points at Antichriſtian Popery, <hi>for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſion, to believe a lye, becauſe they received not the Love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved; that they all may be damned, who believe not the Truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. What ſtrange account do their legends give of their pretended Miracles, as the moſt effectual way to gain c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edit to theſe Doctrines, which they ſee can have no poſſible founding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Scripture; ſuch as that we may judge thoſe, who are but in the leaſt knowing amongſt them, wonder, how Credit could be expected from any thereto, ſuch as they tell us of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> how he was greater then <hi>John the Baptist,</hi> and better then all the Apoſtles, who in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion received the Wounds of Chriſt, ſuffered the ſame griefs, in whom all vertues of the Saints, as well under the Old, as under the New Teſtament, ar put <hi>unitivè &amp; conjunctivè,</hi> and after, moſt blaſphemouſly puts him in the ſame roome with our moſt bleſſed Lord, by reaſon of a ſcedule which they ſay <hi>Leo</hi> the Friar ſaw deſcend from Heaven, and fell on the Head of <hi>Francis,</hi> whereon was write, <hi>this man is the grace of God, and example of all perfection,</hi> &amp;c. This Book, wherein theſe; yea where more horride blaſphemies are written, called <hi>liber con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitatum impreſsis Bononiae Fol.</hi> 3, &amp; 250. is called by them their golden book, with this expreſs clauſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath by a general conſent of the Chapter of that Order, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye have ſearched<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this book, and found nothing worthy of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105851:27"/> correction. Such an inſtance alſo is he, whom they call <hi>St Dominick,</hi> of whom they ſhew that Chriſt raiſed three only from the dead, but <hi>S. Dominick,</hi> three in one City that he had the Angels at his Service, (but it may be eaſy to judge what Angels they were) how the Elements did obey him, and the Devils trembled at him: how he had a ſtar in his forehead, when he was Baptized, and reſtored fourty ſtrangers to life that where over whelmed in a ſhip, and long under the water, with much more of this kind; publiſhed to the World by <hi>Anthony</hi> an Archbiſhop of his Order. <hi>Anthon. Arch. Pag.</hi> 3, 23. but with theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous inſtances may be ſitly joined two Nunes, no leſs known and publick, who if they had lived in one time, and their order could have allowed it, might have been ſuteably matcht with other, the one is <hi>Magdalena de Cruce,</hi> Abbeſs of a Monaſtery of Franciſcan Nunnes, who by the Power of the Devil appeared to Mariners in a ſtorme at ſea, when invocate, and the ſtorme calmed, was ſometimes lift up into the air, and the Sacrament went up viſibly out of the Prieſts hand that ſaid Maſs, through the air before all that look on, unto her: was of ſuch repute, that not only many ladies in Spain but the Queen alſo when ſhe was near to be brought to bed, ſent the mantles wherein the Child was to be wrapt, for her to bleſs: yet at length upon cleareſt diſcovery, and her own confeſſion, found to be a witch, in expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact with the Devil ſince ſhe was nine Years old, ſo as the Spaniſh Inquiſitors could not get ſhifted ſome forme of Sentence againſt her Anno 1540. A paſſage, the truth whereof the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> will not offer to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own, the relation being ſo publick and known by their own writers: And indeed ſhe was well ſuted to be an Abbeſs of S, Francis Order. The other Inſtance is that relation ſet forth by one <hi>Stephen de Luſignan</hi> dedicated to the French Queen of the great Miracles in the Year 1586, which hapned to the Prioreſs <hi>de le Annonciado</hi> of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105851:27"/> 
                     <hi>Lisbon in Portugal,</hi> approved by the greateſt Church men there, whoſe names are ſet down, how uſually Chriſt appeared to her, and talked with her, and had the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of his five wounds put upon her, with many ſuch ſtrange things, ſo as ſeverals were incited through the fame of her, to become Nunnes, yet at laſt was by a mervellous providence from the Lord, diſcovered, and all to be an impoſture, confeſſing the ſame her ſelf, with the whole manner of it, ſo as the evidence thereof did enforce the Archbiſhop of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> with the Inquiſition to make ſome ſhew of condemning her, as is printed at <hi>Seville</hi> 1589. but the diſcovery came too late of this, or rather too ſoon for their intereſt; after the relation of her Miracles had gone a broad. Theſe inſtances I only here touch, of which ſo many elſe are known to the world, that it may be ſeene, on what ſignes and lying wonders, this party leanes for the ſupport of their Doctrine, which may not abide the light of the Scripture. But oh! It may be ſad, and amazing in this day, when the truth is ſo clearly ſhewed forth, how ſo much the World ſeemes to have loſt all ſight and impreſſions thereof, yea, turned at that rate Atheiſtical, to be thus impoſed upon, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting to that way, where the baite cannot be more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable then the hook, and where men muſt quite both Religion and Reaſon at once, in getting ſuch a ſtile as this of a <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="consideration">
                  <head>CONSID. IV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOurthly,</hi> Whilſt this ſtrange ſight we have this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us of the Romiſh ſtate and Hierarchy, with that peculiar frame and mould it is caſt in, ſo different from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdomes of the world, of ſuch numerous orders and degrees, reſolving in one Monarch and head the man of ſin; after whom the world ſo long hath wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Let us but ſeriouſly alſo conſider what true account
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105851:28"/> antiquitie, on which they ſo much lean, gives of this way.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How clear and noture, even to admiration is that diſcovery ſo many ages paſt, of this Adverſary, his ſhape, the way and manner of his appearance, and ſo expreſly foretold by the holy Ghoſt, as we now ſee with our eyes in the event, when upon no principles of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or the leaſt of viſible appearances ſuch future emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies could ever been foreſeen, or have entered into mens thoughts, that it may be demonſtrably evident to all, this only could have been revealed by him, to whom all his works are known from the beginning.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As the Scripture ſhewes that early riſe this myſtery of iniquity had, and its beginning to work with the firſt dawnings of Chriſtianity, though then more undiſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and under ground: This we may know alſo, under whoſe hand this monſtruous birth was moſt ripened, and brought forth, to a more Publick View of the World: to wit that horrid and vile wretch <hi>Phocas,</hi> who then uſurped the Empire, and conſpired againſt his Maſter <hi>Mauritius,</hi> and as all Hiſtories of that time ſhewes, what a plague and judgement from the Lord he was to the world, ſo as, its related of a holy man, who then lived, after much wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in prayer with God with ſome ſerious enquiry, why ſuch a vilewretch had been ſet up over the Empire, got in a ſtrange m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nner this anſwere, <hi>quia non inveni pejorem.</hi> Yet this cruel and brutiſh man <hi>Phocas,</hi> as the Popiſh writers themſelves are forced to confeſs, was he, for whom <hi>Gregory</hi> the great by his legate, doth ſo congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his advancement, as he ſummonds the Angels and all the Saints in heaven to rejoice therein. After whoſe death, the ſucceeding Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> did ſo far inſinuate on this Emperiour, as to divide him from the Greek Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, and obtained the granting of that Chartour, upon which their pretended right ſtands, to be univerſal head and Biſhop of the Chriſtian Church; a very obvious ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs being here, for one bloody uſurper, as this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105851:28"/> was, who roſe upon the aſſaſination of that good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and his Children, to make thus way for another; nor a fitter mean could have been found to help the man of ſin to his throne, than this <hi>Phocas,</hi> for which ſee <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</hi> 81. an 603. art. 3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It ſhould be remarkable, that concurrance of things was then for the more full diſcovery of this Adverſary, and of his being revealed to be that man of ſin ſhewed by the holy Ghoſt, 2 Theſ. 2: 3. when their own greateſt writers are enforced to tell, ſince this could not poſſibly be hid, how from the eighth Century, and ſeveral ages after, ſuch as exerced the papal power, were for the moſt part, ſo many prodigies of wickedneſs in their time, that thoſe Hiſtories ſeemes to want words to expreſs the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and abomination of ſuch as were Popes, for which let any but read <hi>Platina</hi> himſelf <hi>lih.</hi> 5. upon <hi>Benedict the</hi> 4. and many others, of their lives, where he ſhewes, how they were become ſuch, as laying aſide all divine Worſhip, like cruel tyrrants did exerce their malice in the world; but that ſome of them lived not long, God taking them away as ſo many Monſters of men: but more fully doth <hi>Cardinal Benno</hi> ſpeak to this, yea <hi>Baronius</hi> alſo in his <hi>Annales Tom.</hi> 10. how it was then known their ordinary uſe of Magick, conſulting with the Devil, and giving themſelves over to theſe horrid Villanies, as no heathen records almoſt give ſuch an account. And, which are <hi>Baronius</hi> his own words, though one of the greateſt friends to the <hi>Popiſh intereſt,</hi> that ſuch was the face of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> as <hi>Sees</hi> were changed, Biſhopricks and Church offices given at the pleaſure of the vileſt Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets that then bare rule at Rome. Now this is that true antiquity they have to boaſt of to the world, and of thoſe Popes, whoſe infallibility in all matters of faith they would perſwade men to rely on.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. How undeniable is it from thoſe times, when the <hi>Romiſh Hierarchy</hi> once began to ripen to its height,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105851:29"/> what ſoreſt plagues did thus follow and break in on the Chriſtian world, yea, what an inlet of groſſeſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance was therewith, not only of divine things, but of all humane literature, and morality; as from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currance of hiſtories then is clear; that with the ſeveral ſteps of the advance of the Popiſh grandour and power, the world did gradually turne worſe, yea, and in a ſtrange manner became barbarous, rude and ſavage, ſo as both <hi>Baronius</hi> and others of their writers, (who, they know intended no reflection upon their way, further then neceſſity enforced them to ſpeak) ſhewes, ſuch was the face of thoſe times, as it was a matter of ſuſpition to know the Greek language, but to have any knowledge of the Hebrew, was no leſs than hereſie; yea calleth them <hi>infaeliciſſima &amp; luctuoſiſſima Romanae Eccleſiae tempora,</hi> and that theſe and following ages were ſuch, wherein all things both humane and divine, were in viſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And is it not noture to all, who conſults the Church records what a flood not only in diſſolutneſs of practice, but Atheiſme in Principles did remarkeably then break forth on the Chriſtian world, with that advance of the <hi>Romiſh intereſt</hi> towards its height; ſo as thoſe, who were ſerious in the matters of truth, were almoſt brought to a queſtioning of the whole of the Goſpel, and any ſound founding of their faith in the matters of God, whilſt Religion ſeemed to be almoſt loſt in fabulous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and humane inventions, thus <hi>Fredrick</hi> the <hi>third King of Suily,</hi> a religious Prince in ſuch dark times, was ſtaggered about the Chriſtian faith, and made to queſtion if the Goſpel was not ſome humane device, as is publiſhed at length in his conference with <hi>Arnoldus</hi> de <hi>Villanova</hi> a learned man, upon theſe grounds. 1. That the whole Clergy great and ſmall conformed their lives no wiſe to the Scripture, had no regard to the ſouls of the people, and diſcharged ſacred offices, for a forme only,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105851:29"/> or elſe in ſcorne and mockery, which then was ſo noture, as it could not be hid. 2. That thoſe of the more ſevere order of Monks did obviouſly evidence hypocriſy, impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wantonneſs, rapine, yea incredulity about the Goſpel it ſelf. 3. That in a Doctrine ſo weighty, and of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as the Chriſtian faith, the Romish Church ſeemed ſo little concerned, were intangled in worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and no courſe ſet on foot for propagation of the Goſpel, to ſatisfy whom <hi>Arnoldus</hi> shewed, how expreſly ſuch defection, and theſe corruptions were foretold under the New Teſtament, as that conference published by him ſelf shewes. And beſides, it is known what advantage the viſible groſneſs of Popery gave to <hi>Mahumidaniſme,</hi> and for many's falling off from the viſible Profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; which cauſed <hi>Averroes</hi> the Philoſopher to cry out, <hi>Cum Chriſtiani Deum ſuum manducent, ſit anima mea cum Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophis.</hi> Yea enforced ſuch, who gave any ſerious look to the Scripture, to ſay, that either the Scripture was not the Word of God, or ſuch as profeſſed the ſame, were not Chriſtians. And when thus Atheiſme may be ſeene to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Popery</hi> as its native effect, and mutually concurre toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Oh! what might be feared from ſuch an obvious conjunction of both in this time, if the truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God were not his Churches ſecurity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="consideration">
                  <head>CONSID. V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FIfthly,</hi> Sould it not ſeeme ſtrange, and ſuch, as no reaſon can truely anſwere, why in theſe times Kings &amp; great men of the earth hath given their power to ſupport the <hi>Romish interest,</hi> when this ſo viſibly is deſtructive to the juſt right, and intereſt of all Magiſtrats; but that we ſee it is of God, in giving than ſo far up in his ſecret judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, until the Scripture be fulfilled, as is clear, Rev. 17: 17. for Its ſure, otherwiſe theſe things can not be hid from their eyes.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105851:30"/>1. That as the grandour of the Romish Church grew up, how the Kings of the earth by giving their power thereto, loſt their own, and by their concurrace in this deſigne were no leſs evidently depreſſed, than the other raiſed; ſo as all, who look in on the hiſtory of ſuch times, may clearly ſee the ſeveral ſteps of the Popes advance, in coming to his height, and of the Empir's declining and fall, both in the Eaſterne and weſterne parts, moſt viſibly meet in one and the ſame hiſtory: yea thus, how quickly Magiſtracy, and the power thereof was turned to an Image and shadow, that it could not further live and act, but as it was enlivened with the Romish breath, yea, how quickly in a few ages after <hi>Phocas;</hi> the greateſt of the weſterne Emperors were forced to bow at the Popes feet, ſo as <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth</hi> was put to ſtand three dayes in the cold winter barefooted at the Pop's gates, ere he could be reconciled, upon ſome pretended quarrel he had againſt him; yea the Popish writers accounts it their honour to tell the world how <hi>Fredrick Barbaroſſa,</hi> the firſt Emperor of that name, was made to lay his neck under <hi>Pope Alexanders</hi> feet, until he trampled thereon, blaſphemouſly making uſe of that Scripture, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91. that thus he would tread upon the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Dragon:</hi> before he could obtain his ſon's liberty then in priſon in <hi>Venice,</hi> and at the Pop's diſpoſing. And here we may have a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Commentar on that Scripture, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2: 3. that this let, which was to be taken out of the way of the man of ſin's being revealed, as is there foretold, was not the heathen Empire of Rome only, but the Roman Empire in its integrity and ſtrength even after it was Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is undeniable from the Romish Doctrine and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that power the Pope and Rulers of their Church owns to dethrone Kings, and tranferre their Kingdomes to others, and by there Interdiction to looſe ſubjects from any tye or alledgeance to their Prince, to bind or looſe mens conſciences, as they find their own intereſt ſtand; and by that plenitude of their Churches power, to exempt Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105851:30"/> Perſons from the Lawes of Magiſtrats, ſo as they may not be judged by theſe, for the moſt horride and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Crimes, which the Civil Power ought to punish; whilſt their Church immunities are a City of refuge for retreat.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And as the Romish Religion ſtricks at the very roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Piety and Godlineſs, when by the Popes Power, yea of ordinary Prieſts, it can diſpenſe with the moſt horride Acts of wickedneis, murther, adultery, rapts, inceſt, ſodomy, and hath their rates ſtated at what price they can purchaſs a full abſolution for the ſame, ſo doth it thus no leſs viſibly ſtrick at the greateſt ſecurity of Government, and that which foundeth the ſtrongeſt Obligations to all Civil and Moral Duties, which is to have the aw and regard of Religion kept up in a nation.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is clear alſo how the Romish Doctrine ſubverts truth and righteouſneſs amongſt men, which is the greateſt ſecurity of all Perſonal intereſts, when it avowedly warrants equivocation both in Oaths and Words, and in ſuch doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tearmes to ſweare, as may be directly contrair to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the judge requiring the ſame, ſo as an Oath in judgment cannot be the end of controverſy, yea by their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine expreſly teaches alſo, that a man is not bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent preſently for the moſt hainous ſins, but is only neceſſar in the laſt extreame of Life.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Are not the Principles of the Romish Religion ſuch as are viſibly deſtructive even to humane ſociety, in ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed owning, under a pretended zeal againſt hereſy (for ſuch is the Doctrine of Chriſt unto them) thoſe Prodigies of cruelty, which we should think humane nature, though corrupt, could not but tremble at, without being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the very image of the Devil? Such as the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Irish Maſſacres,</hi> the <hi>Netherland</hi> perſecution under the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alva,</hi> the <hi>Spanish Inquiſition,</hi> and thoſe bloody years under <hi>Queene Mary's</hi> reigne in <hi>England,</hi> do before all the world witneſs; yea, its obvious, how no cruelty, even
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105851:31"/> of the Heathens in the firſt times of the Church can almoſt be found to parallel with Popish cruelty, where they can have a doore opened for this. Oh! That it should be ſo little ſeen and laid to heart at this day, how the common intereſt and concerne of all Princes and Magiſtrats, even upon their own civil rights, is to contend againſt this greateſt adverſary, that ever Jeſus Chriſt had upon the earth, and if now be not believed, ſaddeſt experience may yet make this clear, that in thoſe parts, where the truth hath been received and embraced, and by the good hand of the Lord reſcued from the yoke and dominion of Antichriſt, that its ſure, the ſecurity of the Church and Commonwealth is there neceſſarily conjoyned ſo, that if the Proteſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt should weare out, and the truth decline, the land cannot poſſibly be ſafe, where once this had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
                  <p>The Romish intereſt now ſeemes to gain ground, yea a ſtrange and unuſual conju<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction to promote that way; but its well, we know a more bleſſed and infallible ſecurity, than outward appearances to reſt upon: and with that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, as we can be perſwaded of an eternal ſalvation by Jeſus Chriſt. It is ſure alſo. 1. That the victory and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of this warre shall be on the Lambs ſide, and thoſe that are with him muſt overcome, when the living God hath paſt his word thereupon, to his Church; and though we may ſet no bounds, as to any particular time, we have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lide ground to believe that a more remarkeable ſtroke, above all that hath been hitherto, haſteneth upon the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt. 2. That who ſoever withdraw, and think it their intereſt now to keep a diſtance in any adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing for the truth, yet light and deliverance shall ariſe to the Church from another airth; but this shall not be their eſcape and outgate: Yea though it ſeeme a ſtrange contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to ſenſe and reaſon, it is to be the matter of our faith, that aſſuredly now the riſe and advance of the reformed Church is on foot, and her sharpeſt conflicts and wreſtlings
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105851:31"/> muſt tend thereunto. 3. Though the Spirit of interceſſion and prayer may be too diſcernably found under a ſad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, as to what hath been in former times in the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet this ſure, that many prayers and groans once put up by an innumerable company who now are in heaven, in behalf of the Church, and for that ſolemne day of Babylons fall, yet waits and ſtill cryes before the throne; ſuch prayers, wherein they had greateſt acceſs and liberty by the help of the Spirit, for powring out their ſouls thus before the Lord. 4. It's ſure we are to believe, that inſtruments shall be yet raiſed, and called for that end with a mervelous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God upon them, to execute the judgment written againſt this Adverſary; and O what a bleſſed, and honourable ſervice shall it be? 5. Should this not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be made out, but through a ſea of blood, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heads over many Countries, yea in a way (as we have cleareſt ground to judge) which humane reaſon could never reach. It is ſure, this cannot be wanting, and when the God of truth hath ſaid, ſuch an enemy shall be brought down, his Counſel muſt ſtand, though all the Kingdomes of the earth ſtood in the way thereof; Oh! at what a rate does theſe now run themſelves in the way of his wrath and vengeance, and to be partakers of the ſame plagues with Antichriſt, who yet will not ceaſe, for giving their power to ſupport that accurſed and falling intereſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>squirrel eating</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
